<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true history of the Roman Catholicks designs and bloody contrivances for the subversion of the Protestant religion in England. And how by the wonderful providence of God their treasonable and bloody conspiracies and designs have been discovered and prevented.</title>
            <author>Thou, Jacques-Auguste de, 1553-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1077A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185008</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077678</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077678</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151791</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94307)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151791)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2277:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true history of the Roman Catholicks designs and bloody contrivances for the subversion of the Protestant religion in England. And how by the wonderful providence of God their treasonable and bloody conspiracies and designs have been discovered and prevented.</title>
                  <author>Thou, Jacques-Auguste de, 1553-1617.</author>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 19 [i.e. 66] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Leigh at the Sign of the Blew Bell by Flying-Horse Court in Fleet-Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated by Edward Stephens [i.e., Socrates Christianus]. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Added t.p. has date: 1674.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 66 numbered 19.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 19 [i.e. 66].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coligny, Gaspard de, --  seigneur de Châtillon, 1519-1572.</term>
               <term>Huguenots --  France.</term>
               <term>Saint Bartholomew's Day, Massacre of, France, 1572.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="misleading_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151791:1"/>
            <p>A TRUE HISTORY OF THE Roman Catholicks <hi>DESIGNS</hi> And Bloody Contrivances for the Subverſion of the Proteſtant Religion IN ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>And how by the wonderful Providence of God their Treaſonable and Bloody Conſpiracies and Deſigns have been diſcovered and prevented.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Leigh</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Blew Bell</hi> by <hi>Flying-Horſe</hi> Court in <hi>Fleet-Street.</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151791:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151791:2"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE Bloody Maſſacres OF THE PROTESTANTS IN FRANCE IN THE Year of our LORD, 1572.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN In Latin by the Famous <hi>HISTORIAN J A. A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>G. TH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and faithfully rendred into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>John Leigh</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Blew-Bell</hi> by <hi>Flying-horſe</hi>-Court in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:151791:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151791:3"/>
            <head>A brief Introduction to the Hiſtory of the MASSACRE.</head>
            <p>THE Lords of the Houſe of Guiſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the inſtigation of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, whom they firſt introduced into France, and highly favoured, or through their emulation<note n="*" place="margin">V. Diſcourſe, ſect. 40.</note> againſt the Princes of the Blood who favoured the Reformed Religion, or both, profeſſing themſelves great zealots for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Authority, and irreconcilable enemies to the Hugonots, (as they called them of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion) eſpecially after the diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons grew high between them and the Princes, to whom they doubted not but the Proteſtants would adhere, as well upon the account of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as of the Right of the Princes, having<note n="*" place="margin">V. Diſc. ſect. 41.</note> by force gotten the young King Charles <hi>9.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hands, endeavoured by all means to raiſe in his mind as great prejudice and hatred againſt the Proteſtants and the chief men of
<pb facs="tcp:151791:4"/>their party as poſſible. The young King thus trained up in prejudice againſt them, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over from his youth inured to cruelty, and the ſlaughters of his Subjects even in cold blood, whereof by the D. of Guiſe he had been early made a ſpectator, was ſcarce out of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority when he was ivited by the Pope,<note place="margin">V. Diſc. ſect. 42.</note> the K. of Spain, and the D. of Savoy to joyn in a holy League for the extirpation of the Hereticks: but being by nature of an Italian genius, and well inſtructed by his Mother in the policies of her Country, he choſe as a more ſafe and ſurer way to attempt that rather by ſecret ſtratagems and ſurprize than by open hoſtility. And therefore at an <hi>enterview at Bayonne</hi> between him with his Mother, and his Siſter the Queen of Spain accompanied with the D. of Alva, having by the way had ſecret conference at Avignon with ſome of the Pope's truſty Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (the Pope having perſwaded that meeting, and earneſtly preſſed the King of Spain himſelf to be preſent at it) it was concluded to cut off the chief heads of the Proteſtants, and then, in imitation of the Sicilian Veſpers, to ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the reſt to the laſt man. But the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
<pb facs="tcp:151791:4"/>being diſcovered to the Prince of Conde, Colinius and others of the Nobility, when they perceived ſuch preparations made for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it, as, unleſs timely prevented, they were likely ſuddenly to be all deſtroyed,<note place="margin">V. Diſc. ſect. 43.</note> they put themſelves into a poſture of defence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon broke out a Civil War. But that being contrary to the deſign to effect the buſineſs by stratagem and ſurprize, it was in few months compoſed for the preſent; but ſhortly after, when the ſame deſign was again perceived to be carried on, and the like inevitable danger approached as neer as before, was again renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the former manner, and continued ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what longer and hotter than before.<note place="margin">V. Diſc. ſect. 45.</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the King perceiving that the greateſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty was to beget and confirm in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Nobility a truſt and confidence in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, uſed all arts imaginable to do that; and to that purpoſe in all ſolemn manner granting and confirming to the Protestants in France very fair terms of peace and ſecurity, he at the ſame time pretended a reſolution to make a war with Spain, entred into a League with the Queen of England, and with the Proteſtant
<pb facs="tcp:151791:5"/>Princes of Germany; and, which was the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of the policy, propoſed a match be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Prince of Navar, the firſt Prince of the Blood, and chief of the Proteſtant Party, and his Siſter Margaret, as that which would not only ſerve his purpoſe to beget a confidence in the Proteſtants of his ſincerity and good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, but moreover afford him a fair opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity at the ſolemnization of the Marriage, of effecting his deſign at laſt, which had been ſo often and ſo long diſappointed. All which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving managed with wonderful art and diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, be at laſt obtained what he deſired, as in the following Hiſtory is more particularly related.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151791:5"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF THE MASSACRES OF THE Proteſtants at PARIS, and many other places in FRANCE, in the Year of our Lord, 1572.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. THE day of the Nuptials <hi>[between Henr.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>King of Navar and Margaret Siſter to the King of France]</hi> drawing on; which was appointed the<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt <hi>18th.</hi>
                  </note> 15th. of the Kalends of September; the King by Letters ſolicits Coligni, that he ſhould come to Paris, having before given in charge to Claudius Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus Provoſt of the Merchants, that he ſhould ſee to it, that no diſturbance did ariſe upon Colignie's coming to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151791:6"/>Likewiſe <hi>Proclamation</hi> was <hi>publiſhed</hi> the third of the Nones of July,<note place="margin">July 5th.</note> when he was at <hi>Caſtrum-Bononiae,</hi> about two miles from the City, wherein it was forbidden, that any of what condition ſoever ſhould dare to renew the memory of things paſt, give occaſion of new quarrels, carry piſtols, fight duels, draw their ſwords, eſpecially in the King's retinue at Paris, and in the Suburbs, upon pain of death. But if any difference ſhould ariſe among the Nobles concerning their Honour or Reputation, they ſhould be bound to bring their plaint to the Duke of Anjou, the King's Deputy throughout the whole Kingdom, and to pray juſtice of him: if they were of the Commons, they ſhould betake themſelves to the High Chancellor de l'Hoſpital: if it, ſhall happen among thoſe that ſhall not be in the Court, but in Paris, they ſhall go before the ordinary Magiſtrate. It was alſo provided by the ſame Proclamation, that thoſe who were not of the Courts of any of the Princes or Nobles, or of the Retinue of others, or were not detained upon ſome neceſſary buſineſs, but were of uncertain abode and habitation about Paris or the Suburbs, ſhould depart from the Court &amp; City within 24 hours after the publication of this Edict, upon the ſame pain of death. This was publiſhed for three days together, with the ſound of Trumpet in the Court, and through the City, and it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that the publication ſhould be repeated week by week upon the Sabbath-day. Alſo there was adjoyned to the guards of the King's body for his greater ſecurity, a guard of 400 choice Souldiers; all which <hi>Coligni</hi> full of confidence and good aſſurance ſo <hi>interpreted,</hi> as if the King deſirous of the publick Peace, did (only) prepare a contrary ſtrength againſt thoſe which were ſeditious, and movers of troubles. Therefore he <hi>comes into the City,</hi> though <hi>many</hi> were greatly <hi>diſturbed at it:</hi> to whom, when they importunately dehorted him both by letter and word of mouth, he, after he had given them thanks, anſwered in one word; <q>That he was reſolved now that Peace was concluded, and things paſt forgotten, to rely upon the ſaith of the King, and that he had rather be dragged through the ſtreets of Paris, than to take up Civil Arms again.</q>
               </item>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151791:6"/>
               <item>2. Among other <hi>letters</hi> there was one <hi>brought to him</hi> being now come to Paris, written very ſmartly after this manner. <q>Remember that it is an eſtabliſhed Decree of the Papiſts, upon the account of Religion, and confirmed by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Councils, that Faith is not to be kept with hereticks; in the number of which Proteſtants are accounted. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber alſo that Proteſtants upon the account of the former Wars, do lie under an eternal odium; ſo that it is not to be doubted but this is the Queens reſolution, that Proteſtants be rooted out by any means whatſoever. Add to this that it cannot be, but that a woman that is a ſtranger, and an Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, deſcended of the race of the Popes, (whom they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) and of a Florentine and guileful nature, ſhould ſtudy all extremities againſt her enemies. Conſider moreover in what School the King was educated, in which he drew in with his milk under his good Tutors this Doctrine; that he ſhould make it a ſport to ſwear and forſwear, to uſe the name of God profanely, to defile himſelf with Whoredomes and Adulteries, to diſſemble his Faith, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Counſels, to ſet his countenance (according to occaſion). And that he might be accuſtomed to the effuſion of the bloud of his Subjects, he was taught from his childhood to behold the ſlaughters and butcheries of<note n="*" place="margin">And of men alſo, <hi>v. l.</hi> 24. <hi>p.</hi> 275.</note> beaſts: that he is ſetled in this perſwaſion to ſuffer no Religion in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom but that which may uphold his ſtate, (according to the opinion of his Maſter Machiavel) otherwiſe it would never be at Peace, ſo long as two Religions flouriſhed in it, and that it was inſtilled into his ears that the Proteſtants did decree to ſpoil him of his Life and Empire. And therefore he would never ſuffer the Proteſtants who had once, whether upon a juſt or unjuſt cauſe, taken up Arms againſt him, to enjoy the benefit of his Edict, but that he would with Arms revenge what was done with Arms againſt him; nor would he look upon himſelf obliged to keep his Covenants which he had entred into with his armed Subjects. Theſe are the Arts of Princes, the Elements of Policy, the Arcana Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii. So Commodus of old commanded Julian, whom he owned and embraced as his Father, to be ſlain. Thus
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151791:7"/>Antonius Caracalla, under pretence of muſtering, ſlew the prime youth of the City. So Lyſander cut the throats of eight hundred Mileſians called together under pretence of friendſhip and ſociety. So Sergius Galba raged upon ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Spaniards: and lately by the command of Antonius Spinola, the chief men of the Iſle of Corſica were called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to a Feaſt, and ſlain. In our memory did Chriſtiern a King of a barbarous nature uſe the ſame arts in the Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre of Stockholm. So heretofore Charles 7, though recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to the Duke of Burgundy, yet abſtained not from kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, though he begged for his life. Nor are the diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that the King lately had with his mother at Blois un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known. For when in a jocular manner profanely uſing, as his cuſtom is, the name of God, he asked her whether he had not acted his part handſomely at the coming of the Queen of Navar? the Queen anſwered that he had begun well, but theſe beginnings would little advantage him unleſs he proceeded; But I, ſaid he, with often repeated oaths, will bring them all into your toils. From theſe words, the truth whereof you may be aſſured of, you ought to take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and if you are wiſe get out of the City, and ſo from the Court, as from a moſt filthy ſink, with all the ſpeed as may be.</q>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Coligni</hi> having read this letter, though he was not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle troubled at it, yet that he might not ſeem altogether to neglect the admonitions and intreaties of his friends, made anſwer; <q>That there was no place left for theſe ſuſpitions, that he could never perſwade himſelf that ſo great perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs could enter into ſo good a King, than whom France for this many years never had a better. That Anjou indeed was more averſe to the Proteſtant party, but that hatred would now ceaſe, even out of reſpect to the affinity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with the King of Navar. For the reſt, the League entred into with England, and that which the King was now making with the Proteſtant Princes of the Empire, did ſufficiently ſhew how he ſtood affected to the Proteſtants, when as he would have one of the Sons of the Elector Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine in his retinue: and ſome one of the Engliſh Nobles,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151791:7"/>as Leiceſter or Burgleii, who were moſt forward for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Moreover he had given his Faith to the Prince of Orange and Naſſau his Brother concerning aids againſt the Spaniards, and that a great ſupply was preparing in the place of thoſe who were routed under Jenlis their leader. That John Galeacius Fulgoſius, who lately returned from Florence, did aſſure them, that Coſunus would lend the King two hundred thouſand Aurei towards that War. That the King's Ambaſſador did carefully pry into the counſels of the Duke of Alva, and daily acquaint the King with them. That this he knew every day from the King. That the Navy that Philip Stroſſy and Polinius Garda do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand at Broage, and upon the Coaſts of Poictou was not prepared to any other uſe but to diſturb the Spaniſh Fleet, which being done, it ſhall go to help the Prince of Orange at Fluſhing. As for himſelf and his own particular ſafety, all might be ſecure of that; for that he through the King's means is reconciled to the Guiſes, each engaging their Faith to the King, that they would neither of them hereafter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach one the other. Laſtly, that the King did all he could to make Peace at home and War abroad, and that he might transfer the War into the Low-Countreys, and againſt the Spaniards. Wherefore he prayed the Author of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and others that are of his mind, that they would no more with theſe ſuſpitions trouble his mind, which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with more weighty buſineſſes, and better deſigns, but rather that they would, joyning their prayers with his, beg of God that he would proſper things ſo well begun, and bring them at laſt to an happy end, for the good of the Church and Kingdom.</q>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>The ſame things</hi> were <hi>written to Coligni from the Rochel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> which he did in as friendly manner take off with all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and conſtancy. Therefore when they could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him from that mind, they ſet upon <hi>the King of Navar</hi> with Letters dated 6 of the Eids of July,<note place="margin">July <hi>10th.</hi>
                  </note> in which they <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort him</hi> upon the ſame accounts, that he ſhould take care of himſelf, and not go to Paris. He was then, at the Nuptials<note n="†" place="margin">Vid. l. <hi>50.</hi> p. <hi>787.</hi>
                  </note> of Henricus Condaeus his Unckle's Son, and Mary of Cleve
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151791:8"/>his near Kinſwoman, which were celebrated at Blandia a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Jo. Roan Marchioneſs of Rotelin, who was Mother to Frances of Aurleans<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. l. <hi>35.</hi> p. <hi>559.</hi>
                  </note> laſt Wife to Lewis of Conde, within the juriſdiction of Melun. Therefore he deſpiſing the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of his Friends, the Nuptials of the Prince of Conde being finiſhed, <hi>comes to Paris</hi> with him, and a great retinue of Proteſtants in the beginning of Auguſt, where <hi>new delays</hi> are purpoſely invented by the Queen; for whereas at firſt there was hope given of favour to be obtained from the Pope by the Cardinal of Lorain, who was then at Rome, to remove the obſtacle of proximity and difference in Religion, a Breve was brought to Charles Cardinal of Burbon, deſigned to finiſh the buſineſs; wherewith notwithſtanding he ſaid he he was not ſatisfied: therefore he deſired another more full might be ſent from Rome, wherein it might be more amply provided for him. Therefore the King laid the fault of the delay upon the Cardinal of Burbon, who he ſaid, by way of ſcorn, was tied up by ſuperſtition, and I know not what ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of conſcience; and by that means great injury was done to his Margarite (ſo he called his Siſter) who bore it very impatiently to have the fruit of her ſo long expected joy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred.</item>
               <item>5. When in the mean time <hi>Coligni preſſed that the publick proclaiming of the Low-Countrey War</hi> ſo often deliberated about, and approved of, and now whether he would or not begun, might be no longer deferred, he again made delays, and declined it, and often replied to him, importuning him, that he had not any Counſellor or Officer of his Army to whoſe faithfulneſs, induſtry and diligence he could commit ſo great an affair. For ſome were wholly addicted to the party of the Guiſes; others had other faults of their own: of his Secretaries there was only Bernardus Fiza whom he could entruſt with this ſecret. At laſt it was agreed that the affair ſhould be committed to Momorancy and Fiza: with which ſhews of unfeigned familiarity, as he took it, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous freedom, Coligni being deceived, would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelf any thing otherwiſe than of truly Kingly vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or think hardly of the moſt excellent King.</item>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151791:8"/>
               <item>6. Amidſt theſe delays (thoſe) things, as it ſhould ſeem, being altogether compoſed, about which before there was a difference among the Conſpirators, there came <hi>Letters</hi> by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret comport <hi>from the King's Ambaſſador with the Pope,</hi> in which the King is certified of a diſpenſation now granted, and ſhortly to be ſent from Rome by Poſt, wherein the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous conſcience of Burbon was fully ſatisfied: therefore when, upon the <hi>16th.</hi> of the Kalends of September,<note place="margin">Auguſt <hi>17th.</hi>
                  </note> they were <hi>contracted</hi> by Cardinal Borbon in the Louvre, the next day after <hi>the Nuptials</hi> were <hi>celebrated.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>An high Scaffold is erected before the gates of the great Church, by which they deſcended by ſtairs unto a lower Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, which being on every ſide railed in to keep off the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, did lead through the Church to the inner apartment commonly called the Chore. From thence another Scaffold encompaſſed with rails did receive thoſe that went out of the Chore toward the left gate, which reached to the Biſhop's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; thither came out of the Louvre with all Royal Pomp, and moſt magnificent ſhew, the King, the Queen-Mother, with the Brethren the Dukes of Anjou and Alanſon, the Guiſes, the Colonels of the Horſe, the chief Peers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom leading along the Bride, who lodged that night in the Biſhop's Palace. And from the other part, the King of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var, with the Princes of Conde and Contie his Couſins, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligni Admiral of the Sea, Franciſcus Count de la Roche-fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eault, and a great company of the Proteſtant Nobles, who came together out of all Provinces of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>When the King had aſcended to that higher Scaffold, the Ceremonies in manner as was agreed being performed by Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Borbon, the King and Navar with his Party came by the lower Scaffold into the Chore, where having placed his Wife before the great Altar to hear Maſs, he with Coligni and Count de la Roche-fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eault, and the other Nobles of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue went into the Biſhop's Palace by the contrary door afore-mentioned; from whence after Maſs was ended, being recalled by D'Anvil, he came into the Chore again, and kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his new Bride before the King, Queen, and the Brethren, when they had entertained one another ſome little while with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151791:9"/>diſcourſe, they returned into the Biſhop's Palace, where din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was provided. And I well remember when as Maſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, I was admitted through the rails into the Chore, and ſtanding nigh to Coligni, while I fixed my eyes upon him, and curiouſly obſerved him, I heard him ſay, diſcourſing with d'Anville, and looking up to the Enſigns faſtned up and down, and the ſad Monuments of the Battel of Baſſac and Moncountour, <q>That ere long theſe being taken down, others more pleaſing ſhould be ſet up in their places:</q> which words, then he meant of the Low-Country War, which as he thought was now reſolved upon, others interpreted as though he had thoughts of a new Civil War, which he ſo much abhorred.</p>
            <p n="7">7. After Dinner they went into the Palace, where a royal Supper was prepared, and all orders of the City and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, together with the Courts of Accounts, Cuſtoms and Treaſury are entertained according as is uſual in a moſt ſumptuous manner: a ſhort time was ſpent in dancing; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>interludes</hi> were brought in. The repreſentation of three Rocks ſilvered over, upon which the three Brethren, the King, the Duke of Anjou, and Duke of Alanſon did ſit, and ſeven more, upon which Gods and Sea-monſters were ſet, which followed, being drawn along in Coaches, and were brought through the great Hall of the Palace, which was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by a triumphal arch in the middle, and when they made a ſtand, ſome choice Muſitians recited Verſes in their own Tongue, compoſed by the beſt of their Poets. And thus a great part of the night being ſpent in interludes, they after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards betook themſelves to their reſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>next day</hi> being not able to riſe before the Sun was got high, at three a clock after-noon they went to dinner at the Duke of Anjou's Palace, where after dancing they went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the evening to the Louvre.</p>
            <p>The <hi>day following</hi> being <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> running at Tilt, and <hi>interludes</hi> which had been a long while in preparing, were <hi>exhibited at the Cardinal Bourbon's Palace:</hi> there were repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented upon the right hand the Manſions of the bleſſed, and a little below the Elyſian-fields poſſeſſed by 12 Nymphs, on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151791:9"/>the other ſide on the left-hand was repreſented Hell flaming with fire and brimſtone, and full of ſprights and frightful ghoſts. The Brethren, the King, the Duke of Anjou, and the Duke of Alanſon defended Paradiſe as they called it: which many Knights Errant ſeeking to break into, of whom Navar was Captain; they were every one of them repulſed, and at laſt thrown headlong down into Hell. Then Mercury riding upon a Cock, and together with him Cupid came ſliding down to the defendants, and then after much diſcourſe with them returned into Heaven. Then the three defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants came to the Nymphs wandring in the pleaſant green fields, and led them into the middle of the Hall, where the Spectators were with much pleaſure entertained with new Dances about the Fountain for a full hour. Then the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants being prevailed upon by their entreaties, the Knights Errant that were ſhut up in Hell were releaſed; who preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a confuſed skirmiſh break their ſpears: at laſt the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder that was laid by pipes about the Fountain being fired, fire broak forth with a great noiſe, and conſumed all their Scenes, and ſo all departed.</p>
            <p>This ſhew was variouſly interpreted, for that the aſſailants who were moſt of them Proteſtants, did in vain attempt to get into the ſeats of the bleſſed, and were afterwards thruſt down into Hell: for ſo they put a mockery upon the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and others did bode that it portended ſome miſchief. However, certain it is, that <hi>Francis E. of Momorancy,</hi> whether ſuſpecting ſome evil, or being indiſpoſed by reaſon of the toſſing of the Sea, as lately returned from his Ambaſſy in England, having obtained leave of the King, <hi>went to Chantilly</hi> for his healths ſake; leaving in the Court Henry d'Anville, Carolus Meruvius, and Gulielmus Thoraeus (his) Brethren, and that very happily for that moſt Illuſtrious Family:<note place="margin">V. Da. p. <hi>370.</hi>
               </note> for it was the general opinion, that the plotters of the following Maſſacre would have comprehended them all in this conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, had they not feared that Momorancy, who was now ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, would have revenged it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>next day</hi> being <hi>Thurſday,</hi> there was running at <hi>Tilts</hi> held in the Court-yard of the Louvre, in which on the one
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151791:10"/>ſide the King and his Brethren, together with the Duke of Guiſe, and the Duke of Aumale in the habit of Amazons; and on the other ſide the King of Navar, with his party in Turkiſh habits, contended with their launces; Scaffolds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet up on either ſide, from which the Queen-Mother, the King's Wife, Lorain, and all the Court-Ladies beheld the ſports.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Two days before the Counſel concerning the Maſſacre being not yet concluded, <hi>the King</hi> with great ſhew of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>beſpeaks Coligni</hi> (thus). <q>You know, Father, (ſo he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him upon the account of his age and honour) what you undertook to me, that you would offer no injury, ſo long as you are at Court, to the Guiſes: and they again engaged, that they, as they ought, would behave themſelves toward you and yours honourably and modeſtly. I repoſe very great truſt in your words, but I have not the like confidence in their promiſes. For, beſides that I know the Guiſes do by all means ſeek revenge, I know their daring and haughty nature, and in what favour they are with the people of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. It would be a very great grief to me, if they who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of coming to the Marriage, have brought with them a great party of ſouldiers well appointed, ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing to your hurt; for that would be an injury to my ſelf: Therefore, if you think it expedient, I think it convenient, <hi>that the Regiment of the Guards be drawn into the City</hi> under theſe Commanders, (then he named thoſe who were no way ſuſpected), who, if any turbulent perſons at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing, may be ready at hand to ſecure the publick Peace.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To ſuch friendly diſcourſe Coligni eaſily yielded his aſſent out of a deſire of domeſtick Peace, and being already over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the Court-flatteries: therefore a Regiment is drawn within the walls, without any ſuſpition of the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p n="9">9. This being done, <hi>they enter into Counſel</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 51. He mentions a former Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation between the Queen-Mother, Anjou, Cardinal Lorain, Aumale, Guiſe, Birage, and others in the ſame Chamber, wherein Guiſe was afterwards by the King's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand killed, and afterwards in the ſame buildings where the King himſelf Henr. 3. here called Anjou, was murthered by a Fryer.</note> 
               <hi>again,</hi> and after ſome debate the thing was left undetermined, their opinions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151791:10"/>varying according to the condition of places, and of the perſons admitted to the Council. For thus it was diſcourſed <hi>before the King,</hi> with whom were in Council the Queen-Mother, the Duke of Anjou, and others.</p>
            <p>
               <q>There are <hi>two factions</hi> in the Kingdom; one of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morancies, to whom the Colignies were formerly added, but now upon the account of Religion, by which they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged many (to them), they conſtitute <hi>a new faction.</hi> The other is of the Guiſes: nor will France ever be quiet, or that Majeſty that is taken from Kings by the Civil Wars thence ariſing, ever be reſtored till the chief of their Heads who diſturb the moſt flouriſhing Empire, and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace, be ſtricken off. They, by the troubles of the Kingdom, have grown to ſo great Power, that they cannot be taken away at the ſame time: they are <hi>ſeverally to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, and ſet one againſt the other,</hi> that they may deſtroy one another. Coligni muſt be begun with who only ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives of his Family, who being taken out of the way, it would much weaken the Momorancies, who lie under ſo great an odium upon the account of their joyning with Coligni. But this is an unworthy thing, and not to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by you, (ſaid they, directing their diſcourſe to the King), that a man whom only Nobility commends, one that is advanced to honour by the favour of Kings, now grown burdenſom to the Nobility, equal to Princes in honour, grievous to your ſelf, ſhould come to that height of madneſs and boldneſs, that he ſhould count it a ſport to mock at Royal Majeſty, and every day at his own luſt to raiſe Wars in the Kingdom. Certainly his madneſs is above all things by you, if you be indeed King, to be reſtrained, that by his example all may learn to bear their fortunes decently, and uſe them modeſtly. Nor only ſhall the faction of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morances be broken by his death, but the power of the Proteſtants ſhall be over-turned: of which, when he is the very heart and ſoul, in him alone the Proteſtants ſeem to live, and he being dead, they will fall with him. This is not only uſeful, but neceſſary for ſetling the publick Peace, when as experience doth ſhew, that as one houſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151791:11"/>not keep two Dogs, nor one tree relieve two Parrots, ſo one and the ſame Kingdom cannot bear two Religions. This may be done without danger or blame, if ſome cut-throat, as there are enough of them to be had, be ſuborned to take away the life of Coligni, encouraged by ſome preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and hopes of future; who having done the thing, may make his eſcape by the help of a light horſe prepared for that purpoſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V. Dav. p</hi> 368, 370 The opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gondi Coun. of Retz.</note> For then, without doubt, the Proteſtants, who are very numerous in the City, ſuppoſing it to be done by the Guiſes, will preſently, as you know they are a furious ſort of people, take up Arms, and ſetting upon the Guiſians, they ſhall eaſily be cut off by their greater numbers; (for the people of Paris are much addicted to them), and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Momorances ſo hateful to the Pariſians, ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in the ſame tumult. But if the thing proceed not ſo far, yet at leaſt the blame of the fact, from which you ſhall receive great advantage, ſhall be tranſlated from you upon the Guiſians, (as bearing yet in memory the murder of their Father) whom, having deſtroyed their Rivals, you ſhall ſoon reduce into good order. This thing being done, you ſhall forthwith be able to determine concerning the chief leaders of the Proteſtants, whom you have in your power, who, no doubt, will return to their old Religion, and due allegiance to you when evil Counſellors ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And when it was debated in <hi>the Queens Council</hi> among thoſe that were to be truſted, their diſcourſe went further, that not only the Momorances with Coligni ſhould be taken off, but that the Guiſians ſhould at ſome fit opportunity be ſlain, as thoſe whom the Queen ought in no wiſe to truſt or ſpare, being heretofore grievouſly and often offended by her. For ſo the Counſellors ordered the matter, if the Proteſtants ſhould go about to revenge the death of Coligni, they and the Momorances ſhould in the conflict be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the people, as being inferior in ſtrength, but not without great loſs to the adverſaries; whom the King having drawn a great number of Souldiers, which he had then at his command, into the Louvre, ſitting as a ſpectator, might at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151791:11"/>laſt ſet upon, being broken, and weakened by ſighting, and as though they had taken Arms without his command, and by way of ſedition, might command them all to be ſlain together with the Nobles, as taking this or that party: for whiles they remained ſafe, there would be no end of murmurs and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt the Queen; whom the ſeditious cry out upon as a ſtranger, and ſo ſit to be removed from the Government of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Theſe were their divers counſels according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of the perſons, but they all agreed in the executing of the matter. The Duke of Guiſe being at laſt taken into the privity of the fact, though otherwiſe he knew nothing of the other Counſels, <hi>an Aſſaſine</hi> was ſought for, and preſently <hi>Morevell</hi> appears, being as it ſeemed provided for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; who having formerly undertaken to do ſuch a villany, he fled into the Camp of the Proteſtants, but being affrighted by the danger of it, leſt he ſhould ſeem to have done nothing, he treacherouſly ſlew Arthurus Valdraeus Moius,<note place="margin">Monſieur de Muy at the ſiege of Niort. Dav. p. <hi>376.</hi>
               </note> and from that time often changing his lodgings, he concealed himſelf in the houſe of the Guiſes, in which Family he was brought up from a child. An houſe was alſo pitched upon in the Cloyſter of St. German Auxerrois, as they call it, the houſe of Peter Pila Villemur, who had formerly been Tutor to the Duke of Guiſe himſelf; by which Coligni returning home, muſt needs paſs.</p>
            <p>Therefore upon the <hi>Friday, Coligni</hi> having diſpatched much buſineſs in the King's Council, where Anjou was preſent, and compoſed a difference between Antonius, Marafinus, Guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius and Tiangius, chief of the Nobility of the Burgundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, forward men; he attended upon the King to the next Tennis-Court, from whence, after a promiſe from the King, the Duke of Guiſe and Teligny, betaking himſelf home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, walking on foot by the houſe of Villemur, going gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly along, and reading a Petition which was then by chance preſented to him, Morevel diſcharging a Muſquet from a window that had a linen Curtain drawn before it, he was <hi>ſhot with a brace of bullets,</hi> whereof one ſtruck off the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finger of his right-hand, and the other wounded him more
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151791:12"/>dangerouſly in his left-arm, while Guerchius was upon his right-hand, and Rochus, Sorbaeus, Prunaeus upon his left, who, as likewiſe all that were there, were exceedingly aſtoniſhed at what was done.</p>
            <p>But he with a countenance not diſturbed, only ſhewed them the houſe whence the bullets came, and preſently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands Armanus, Claromontius, Pilius, and Franciſcus Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinius, that they ſhould go the King, and in his name acquaint him with what was done: then binding up his arm, and leaning upon his domeſticks, he came on foot to his lodging, which was not far off: and when he was adviſed by one of his company that he ſhould ſee to it, whether the bullets wherewith he was wounded were not poiſoned, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that nothing ſhould befall him but what was ordered by God.</p>
            <p>Forthwith they force the houſe whence the ſhot proceeded, and breaking open the dores, found the Muſquet in a lower room. A young maid and a page that were found there, were taken and bound; for Morevel at a back-dore getting upon his horſe, was already fled to St. Antony's Gate, where changing his horſe, and mounting another that was ready for that purpoſe, he made his eſcape.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>The King receiving the news,</hi> as if he had been aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at an unexpected accident, <q>Shall I never, ſaith he, be at quiet?</q> and muſt new troubles alwaies ariſe from day to day? and then throwing his rocket upon the ground, he withdrew into the inner Caſtle. Guiſe leaving the Tennis-Court, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted another way.</p>
            <p>Here all were full of wonder, and many were diſturbed, being troubled in their minds to think what thoſe things would come to. Many, even of thoſe who bare no great good will to Coligny, deteſted the fact. But <hi>Navar and Conde preſently repair to him,</hi> and when as in their preſence he was handled by the Chirurgions, he was heard amidſt all his pain to ſay (only) this. Is this the goodly reconciliation that the King did undertake for? then turning to Moore, Chaplain to the late Queen of Navar, he pronounced theſe words, <q>Ah my Brother, now I know I am beloved of God,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151791:12"/>for that I have received theſe wounds for his moſt holy Names ſake. God grant I may never forget his accuſtomed mercies towards me.</q> But when Ambroſius Paraeus the King's Chirurgeon told him that the Gangreen growing on, his finger muſt be cut off, and did attempt to do it with an inſtrument that had no good edge, though he was forced to open and ſhut the ſhears three times, yet he gave no ſign of ſenſe of his moſt ſharp pain: when he came to his left arm Merlin Conde's Chaplain came in, who when he began to comfort him out of the holy Scriptures, he brake out into theſe words; <q>My God, forſake me not in theſe troubles, nor ceaſe from thy accuſtomed mercies towards me.</q> Then he whiſpered in the ear to one who held up his arm, that he ſhould deliver to Merlin an hundred Aurei to be diſtributed to the poor of the Church of Paris: this I have often heard Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus ſpeak of, almoſt in the ſame words.</p>
            <p>Thence <hi>Navar and Conde go to the King,</hi> and complain of the indignity of the fact; and ſince they and theirs could not be ſecure at Paris, they deſire leave to depart. Upon this the King aggravating the matter to the higheſt, and adding deeper oaths than before, promiſed that he would take ſuch revenge upon the Aſſaſine, the authors and abetters of this fact, as ſhould ſatisfy Coligny and his friends, and ſhould be an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to others for the future: that what was done was as great a grief to him as to any, but ſince what was done could not be undone, he would take the greateſt care that might be for a remedy, and would make all men underſtand that Coligny had the wound, but he had the ſmart: and that they might be eye-witneſſes of this thing, he deſires them that they would not depart out of Paris.</p>
            <p>And he diſcourſing thus, Queen Katharine, who was then preſent, ſeconded, and ſaith, <q>The affront was offered to the King, not to Coligny; and if this villany ſhould not be puniſhed, it would ere long come to that paſs, that they would even dare to ſet upon the King himſelf in his houſe: therefore all means are to be uſed moſt ſharply to revenge ſo great a villany.</q> Theſe words being ſpoken with much heat, and ſeeming indignation, the minds of Navar and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151791:13"/>were ſomewhat appeaſed, who did not believe there was any diſſimulation, ſo that there was not a word more made of their departure out of the City.</p>
            <p>Preſently <hi>ſome</hi> were <hi>ſent to purſue the Aſſaſine,</hi> though none as yet knew who he was. All the gates of the City are ſhut up till ſearch had been made, except two, by which proviſion was brought in, and even they were kept by a guard appointed by the King. In the mean while the maid and the boy that were taken in Villemur's houſe, who was then from home, were examined a part by Chriſtopher Thuanus, and Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Prevotius Morſanus, Preſidents of the Court, and James Viole a Senator: and the maid confeſſed that a few daies ſince Villerius Challius, a ſervant of the Guiſes, brought a Souldier to that houſe, and commended him to her, as if he had been the Maſter of the houſe, being a very near friend and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar acquaintance of his, and that therefore he made uſe, as long as he was there, of Villemur's Chamber and Bed; but what his name was he did induſtriouſly conceal. The boy who had ſerved the Aſſaſine but a few days, ſaid he was ſent by his Maſter, (who diſſembled his name, and called himſelf ſometimes Bolland, ſometimes Bondol the King's Archer) in the morning to Challius, to deſire him from him, that he would have the horſes in readineſs, which he promiſed him. From all which diſcoveries it was yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain who was the Aſſaſine: but when as they both agreed in Challius, it was given in charge to Gaspar Caſtraeus Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeus, Captain of the King's Guard, that he ſhould ſeize him, and bring him forth to examination. Then Letters are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Governors of the Provinces by the King, in which he deteſted the fact, and commanded that they ſhould make it their buſineſs that all might underſtand that it did highly grieve him, and that ere long there ſhould be given a moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere example of ſo great a crime.</p>
            <p>In the mean while <hi>d' Anville, Coſſaeus and Villarius</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals, <hi>viſiting Coligny</hi> about noon, ſaluted him in moſt friendly manner, and <hi>told him</hi> that that they did not come thither to exhort him to patience and fortitude: <q>For that, ſay they, theſe virtues are as it were natural to thee; thou haſt been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151791:13"/>wont to admoniſh others, and therefore wilt not be wanting to thy ſelf. <hi>He anſwering</hi> with a ſmiling countenance, ſaid, I ſpeak truly, and from my heart, death doth nothing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright me. I am ready moſt willingly to render to God that ſpirit which I have received from him, whenſoever he ſhall require it. But I do greatly deſire an opportunity to confer with the King before I depart this life; for I have ſome things to acquaint him with, which concern both him, and the ſafety and honour of the Kingdom, which I am well aſſured none of you dares carry to him.</q> Then d'Anville told him he would willingly acquaint the King with that (his deſire); and having ſo ſaid, he with Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius and Teligny daparted, leaving Coſſaeus there, to whom Coligny ſaid, Do you remember what I ſaid to you a few hours ſince? be wiſe, and take heed to your ſelf. What he meant by theſe words was not underſtood by all.</p>
            <p n="12">12. But when <hi>the King</hi> knew by d'Anville and Teligny his deſire, he in ſhew ſeemed not unwilling to <hi>come to him</hi> about the afternoon. There came together with him the Queen-Mother, with the Brethren, Anjou and Alanſon, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Borbon, Monpenſſer, Nevers, Coſſaeus and Tavanius, Villarius, Meruvius, Thoreus, Momorancies Brethren, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals, Naucaeus and Radeſianus. Theſe being let in, the reſt are by the King's command ſhut out, except Teligny and a Gentleman of the Family, who ſtood at the Chamber-door; here it is publiſhed in writing, that ſome ſecrets were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the King by Coligny, but others deny it, and ſay that the diſcovery of this ſecret was purpoſely hindered by the Queen, leſt the King, whoſe nature ſhe began to diſtruſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mollified, and perſwaded by the word of Coligny, ſhould change his reſolution. That which was openly heard was this, when Coligny gave the King thanks, the King with a ſad and troubled countenance did earneſtly enquire of his ſtate, and did proteſt, that what had happened to him was a very great grief to him. <q>The wound is thine, ſaid he, but the pain is mine. But I ſwear (then according to his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he ſwore) I will ſo ſeverely revenge this injury, that the memory of it ſhall never be blotted out of the minds of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151791:14"/>men. To this <hi>Coligny anſwered,</hi> God is my witneſs, before whoſe tribunal I now ſeem (ready) to ſtand, that I have been all my life long moſt loyal and faithful to your Majeſty, and I always, and with all my heart, deſired that your Kingdom might be moſt flouriſhing and peaceable. And yet I am not ignorant that there have been ſome who have called me Traytor, and Rebel, and a perturber of our Kingdom; but I truſt, God will ſome time or other judg between me &amp; them, before whom I am ready, if it be his pleaſure that I ſhould at this time depart out of this life, to give an account of my faith and obſervance towards you. Moreover, whereas I have been advanced by Henry your Father to many and great honours which your Majeſty hath been pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm to me; I cannot but according to that faith and love that I have for your affairs, deſire that you would not let ſlip ſo notable an opportunity of an happy enterprize, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially now that the breach is already made, and there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tokens and pledges of your mind, as to the Belgick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition; ſo as if the matter now begun be relinquiſhed, it will be very dangerous to your Kingdom. Is it not a moſt unworthy thing that an egg cannot be moved in your Privy Council, but preſently almoſt before it be turned, a meſſenger runneth and reporteth it to the Duke of <hi>Alva?</hi> Is it not a moſt baſe thing that 300 either Gentlemen or gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant ſoldiers taken in Jenlis his ſight, ſhould by the command of Alva either be hanged, or undergo ſome other kind of puniſhment? which thing I do yet perceive to be here in the Court a matter of jeſting and laughing. A third thing which I did deſire to diſcourſe with your Majeſty about, is the contempt of the Pacificatory Edict offered by thoſe that are in place of Juriſdiction, who do in moſt grievous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner daily violate the faith that was given by you; of which faith and oath even foreign Princes are witneſſes. But as I have often told your Majeſty and the Queen-Mother, I do not think there is any ſurer way of preſerving peace and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick tranquility, than by a religious and ſevere obſervance of the Edicts. But they are ſo contemned, that of late at Troyes there was an aſſault made upon the ſervants of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151791:14"/>wife of the Prince of Conde: and when as ſhe, according to the form of your Edict, had choſen a certain Village cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Inſula, in which our Religion ſhould be exerciſed, yet notwithſtanding, of late, a certain man, and a nurſe, and an infant, that was brought to the holy font, were ſlain upon the way whiles they were returning from a Sermon that was made in that place.<note place="margin">Auguſt 10th.</note> And this happened a little before the 4th. Eid, 6 til.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this <hi>the King anſwered.</hi> 
               <q>I eſteem thee, my Father, as I have often aſſured thee for a valiant and faithful perſon, and one that is moſt careful for my honour. Laſtly, I look upon thee as one of the chiefeſt and moſt valiant Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of my Kingdom; nor if I had any other opinion of thee, would I have done what I have for thee. As for the Edict which I lately iſſued out, I have always wiſhed, and do wiſh that it may be moſt diligently obſerved. And to that purpoſe I have taken care that ſome choice perſons ſhould be ſent through the Provinces, that may make this their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; whom if thou doeſt ſuſpect, others ſhall be ſent in their places;</q> (for in diſcourſe he had ſaid he did ſuſpect them who had condemned him to death, and hanging, and ſet a price of fifty thouſand Aurei upon his head). Then, that he might break off this diſcourſe, he added, <q>I ſee, my Father, that you ſpeak earneſtly, and that earneſtneſs may hurt both you and your wounds.</q> I will take care of this affair, (and again, ſwearing by the name of God), <q>I do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you that I will moſt ſeverely revenge this injury upon the Authors of it, as if it were offered to my ſelf.</q> Then he, there is not need of any great ſearch for the Author of the fact, nor are the diſcoveries already made very doubtful. But it is enough, and upon that account, in the moſt humble man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that I can, I give your Majeſty thanks that you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed graciouſly to promiſe me to do me right.</p>
            <p>Then the King taking aſide that Gentleman of the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that ſtood at the dore, commanded him to ſhew him the bullet wherewith Coligny was wounded, and which was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the wound, that he might look upon it. It was a brazen one: then he enquired of him, firſt, whether much
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151791:15"/>bloud flowed out of the wound; next, whether Coligny did ſignify the grievous pains he felt by out-cries and complaints. And having commended his conſtancy, and the greatneſs of his mind, he commanded that Gentleman that he ſhould not depart from him.</p>
            <p>Theſe things paſſed for about the ſpace of an hour in the Chamber of Coligny: the King drawing out the time with wandring diſcourſes, and that he might put off the buſineſs of the Belgick War, to the mention of which, it is obſerved that he made no anſwer. Among theſe diſcourſes Radeſianus ſpoke to a friend of Coligny's concerning the removing him into the Caſtle of the Louvre for his greater ſecurity, if the people ſhould tumultuate; which thing the King himſelf did ſometime repeat, which almoſt all did interpret as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King's care of the health of Coligny. But when the Phyſitians, and chiefly Francis Mazilles the King's chief Phyſitian, anſwered there was danger, if his body ſhould be ſhaken in the carrying whiles his wounds were freſh, he would by no means be removed.</p>
            <p n="13">13. After the King departed, <hi>the Nobles of the Proteſtant party take counſel together,</hi> and John of Ferriers Vidame of Chartres, in the preſence of Navar and Conde, conjecturing what was indeed the matter, ſaid that the Tragedy was begun by the wound of Coligny, but would end in the bloud of them all. Therefore he thought it moſt ſafe, that without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay they ſhould depart the City: he produced teſtimonies and tokens for his opinion from the rumors that were ſpread abroad; for it was heard by many, when upon the day of Marriage the Proteſtants went out of the Church that they might not engage in worſhip; the Papiſts ſaid, by way of mirth, that within a few days they ſhould hear Maſs. Alſo it was openly ſpoken in diſcourſe by the chief of the City, that at that Marriage ſhould be poured out more bloud than wine. That one of the Proteſtant Nobles was adviſed by the preſident of the Senate, that he ſhould with all his family betake himſelf for ſome days into the Country. Beſides theſe things, the counſel of Johannes Monlucius Biſhop of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence (when he was going Ambaſſador into Poland) given
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151791:15"/>to Roch-ſou-cault, that he would not ſuffer himſelf to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated, and turned about by the ſmoke and unwonted fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Court, which deſervedly ought to be ſuſpected by all wiſe and cautious perſons, that he would not be too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to run himſelf into danger, and that he would timely withdraw himſelf, together with other Nobles, from the Court. But Teligny being of another mind, and ſaying that he was abundantly ſatisfied of the ſincere love and good will of the King, Ferrerius, and thoſe that thought as he he did, could not be heard.</p>
            <p>The next day <hi>the Page</hi> was <hi>again examined,</hi> and new wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes produced. In this examination Arnold Cavagnes was engaged, for ſo Coligny did deſire, and all things were done in ſhew, as if there had been a diligent enquiry into the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</p>
            <p>The next day, when as <hi>Coligny, and</hi> by his command <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naton</hi> in the name of his fellows (who, he ſaid, knew for certain that the Pariſians, that is LXM deadly enemies of Coligny would tumultuate, and take Arms), <hi>deſired</hi> of the King and his Brother Anjou, <hi>a guard</hi> of ſome Souldiers to be ſet <hi>to protect the houſe of Coligny,</hi> that if the people ſhould make any diſturbance, they might be reſtrained by fear of the King's guards, they both of them anſwered kindly and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and it was given in command to Coſſenius Colonel of the Regiment of the Guards, that with ſome choice Bands he ſhould keep watch before the dores of Coligny. To theſe were joyned, to avoid ſuſpition, ſome, but few in number, of the Switzers of the guards of Navar. Moreover, for the greater ſecurity, it was ordered by the King, that the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Proteſtants who were in the City, ſhould lodge near Coligny's houſe, and it was given in command to Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-maſters forthwith to aſſign lodgings: and the King gave command with a loud voice, that all might hear it, to one of the Colonels, that no Catholick ſhould be ſuffered to come thither, nor ſhould they ſpare the life of any that ſhould do otherwiſe. Upon this occaſion the Corporals went from place to place, and wrote down the names of Proteſtants, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151791:16"/>adviſed them to repair near to Coligny; for that the King would have it ſo.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like ſigns and whiſperings abroad, though they had been enough to have warned the Proteſtants, if they had not been infatuated; yet by the conſtant diſſimulation of the King it came to paſs, that Coligny and Teligny could not perſwade themſelves that any ſuch cruelty was in his mind. Therefore when <hi>the Nobles entred into conſultation in the Chamber of Cornaton,</hi> in the houſe of Coligny, upon the ſame matter, and the Viſdame of Chartres perſevered in the ſame opinion, that they ſhould depart the City as ſoon as might be, and prevent that imminent danger, though with ſome diſadvantage to Coligny's health, who yet was that day ſomewhat better. Teligny was of opinion, and Navar and Conde agreed with him that they ſhould ſtay in the City, otherwiſe they ſhould offer a great affront to the King, that was ſo well affected towards them.</p>
            <p n="14">14. There was a ſuſpition leſt this ſhould be caried to the King by one that was then preſent, that was Buchavanius Bajancu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, one very familiar with the Queen, who preſently haſted to the Tuilleries, where <hi>a Counſel</hi> was <hi>held by the Conſpirators</hi> under a colour of walking; there was <hi>the laſt time</hi> that they conſulted of the manner of executing the deſign. There were preſent beſides, <hi>the King, Queen,</hi> and <hi>Anjou,</hi> the Dukes of <hi>Nevers</hi> and <hi>Angoleſme,</hi> the Baſtard, <hi>Biragus, Tavannes</hi> and <hi>Radeſianus.</hi> 
               <q>And ſince by the death of one man whom the Phyſitians did affirm was like to recover of his wound, the grievance of the Kingdom, which was nouriſhed by him, and diffuſed into many, could not be extinguiſhed, it ſeemed good that it ſhould be ſuppreſſed by the ruine of all; and that wrath which God would not have to be ſatisfied with the bloud of Coligny alone, ſhould be poured out upon all the Sectaries. That was their voluntary reſolution at firſt, and now by the event, neceſſity and force is put upon their counſels, that the danger that hangs over the King and the whole Kingdom, cannot be avoided without the ruine of Coligny and all the Proteſtants. For what would not he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151791:16"/>do ſo long as the faction of the Rebels remains entire after ſuch an injury? who, when he was no way provoked, was ſo long injurious to the King, and hurtful to the Kingdom? whom now all might foreſee, and dread, going out of Paris with his party, as a Lion out of his den, raging againſt all without reſpect. Therefore the reins are to be let looſe to the people, who are of themſelves ready enough, nor ought they any longer to withſtand the will of God, which would not that more mild Counſels ſhould take effect. After the thing is effected, there will not want reaſons whereby it may be excuſed, the fault being laid upon the Guiſians, which they would gladly take upon them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore all agreed upon the utter ruine of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants by a total ſlaughter. To which opinion the Queen was even by her own nature and proper deſign enclined; ſome time was ſpent in deliberating<note n="*" place="margin">The Duke of Guiſe was ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to have the King of Navar and the Prince of Conde ſlain with the reſt. Dav. p. <hi>370.</hi> It was alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated whether among the reſt they ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the Marſhal d'An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville, and his Brothers, who profeſſed the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but were nearly related to Coligny; but they were ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe the eldeſt Brother Marſhal Momc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancy was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Da. p. <hi>370.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>whether Navar and Conde ſhould be exempt</hi> from the number of the reſt; and as for <hi>Navar,</hi> all their ſuffrages agreed upon the account of his Royal Dignity, and the Affinity that he had lately contracted. For that fact which of it ſelf could not but be blamed by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, would be ſo much the more blamed, if a great Prince near of Bloud to the King, joyned in a very late affinity, ſhould be ſlain in the King's Palace, in the arms as it were of the King his Brother-in-law, and in the embraces of his Wife. For there would be no ſufficient excuſe, nor would thoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments prevail to excuſe the King, which might caſt the blame upon the Guiſians. Concerning <hi>Conde</hi> there was a greater debate, he lying under the load of his Fathers faults: yet both the dignity of the man, and the authority of Ludovicus Gonzaga Duke of Nevers, affirming that he would be loyal and obedient to the King, and alſo offering himſelf as a ſurety for him, upon the account of that cloſe and manifold relation that was between them; (for Conde had lately married Mary of Cleve the Siſter of Henrica Wife of the Duke of Nevers), did prevail that he ſhould be ſpared, and exempt from the number of thoſe that were deſigned for the ſlaughter, as well as Navar.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Upon this the Duke of <hi>Anjou and Engoleſme</hi> the Baſtard
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151791:17"/>departing, as they rode in their Coach through the City, they <hi>ſpread abroad a rumor</hi> as if the King had ſent for Momorarcy and was about to bring him into the City with a ſelect num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of horſe.</p>
            <p>The very ſame hour there was <hi>one apprehended who was ſuſpected of the hurt of Coligny,</hi> who confeſſed himſelf to be a ſervant of the Guiſes; which, when it was underſtood, <hi>Guiſe and Aumale,</hi> and others of the Family went to the King to remove that ſuſpition; and <hi>complain</hi> that they were oppreſſed through the favour that was ſhewed to their enemies: that the ears of Judges were open to calumnies caſt upon them, and that tho they were guiltleſs, yet they were manifeſtly ſet againſt: that they had a long time obſerved that they were, for what cauſe they knew not, every day leſs gracious with the King: but yet that they did diſſemble it, and hoped that time, which is the beſt Maſter of truth, would at laſt inform him more certainly of the whole matter. But ſince they find no place for their innocence, they did, though unwillingly, and as forced to it, <hi>deſire</hi> that with his good leave <hi>they might return home.</hi> This was done openly, and it was obſerved that the King anſwered to theſe things ſomewhat coldly, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he might perſwade the Proteſtants that he bare no good will to the Guiſians.</p>
            <p>Upon this <hi>the King adviſeth Navar</hi> that he ſhould afford no occaſion of miſchief to the audacity and violentneſs of the Guiſians, things being ſo enflamed, and the people enclining to the Guiſian party. That he ſhould command thoſe whom he knew moſt faithful of his ſervants to come into the Louvre, to be ready upon any ſudden accident; which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var did, interpreting it in good part, calling thoſe which were moſt active to lodge with him that night in the Louvre Caſtle.</p>
            <p>Wiſe men alſo did <hi>preſage ſome future commotions,</hi> when they obſerved <hi>armed men</hi> to run up and down about the City and the Louvre, the people to mutter, <hi>threatnings</hi> to be every where heard. This being brought to <hi>Coligny,</hi> he who no way doubted of the good will of the King, but thought it to be the deviſe of the Guiſians to enflame the people, <hi>ſends one
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151791:17"/>to the King,</hi> who ſhould in his name acquaint him with it. To whom the King anſwered, that Coligny need fear nothing: for thoſe things were done by his command, to compoſe the tumults of the people that were ſtirred up by the Guiſians. Therefore, that his mind might be ſecure,</p>
            <p>It was alſo told Teligny the very ſame hour, that <hi>Porters laden with Arms</hi> were ſeen to be brought into the Louvre: but he contemned the meſſage, and anſwered, that unneceſſary ſuſpitions were ſought for in this ſad and diſmal time, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad that this ſhould be made known to Coligny, affecting the unſeaſonable reputation of prudence and moderation, from his deſpiſing of reports, and conſequently of dangers: and excuſing the matter, as if thoſe Arms were carried into the Louvre upon the account of a Caſtle repreſented and aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a ſhew.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Forthwith <hi>Guiſe,</hi> to whom the chief command of the execution of the whole matter was committed, <hi>calling together</hi> in the deep of night <hi>ſome Captains</hi> of the Switzers, and the Captains of the French Troops, <hi>explains to them the Kings will and pleaſure.</hi> 
               <q>That the time was come wherein, by the King's command, puniſhment ſhould be taken upon that head that was ſo hateful both to God and men, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo upon the whole faction of the Rebels: that the beaſt was now in their toils: that they ſhould take care that he eſcape not: that they ſhould not be wanting to ſuch an opportune occaſion, of obtaining a more glorious triumph than they ever yet obtained in all their former Wars, with the bloud of ſo many Royalliſts: that the Victory was eaſy: that rich ſpoils are propoſed, which they might acquire without bloud, as rewards of their good ſervice.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this <hi>the Switzers are placed about the Louvre,</hi> to whom are joyned the French Troops, and command was given that they ſhould look to it, that no man of the Family of Navar or Conde ſhould go out of the Louvre. The keeping of <hi>Coligny's houſe</hi> was <hi>committed to Coſſenius,</hi> to whom was given a party of Muſquetteers to lie in the neighbouring houſes, that none might eſcape them.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151791:18"/>
            <p>Matters being ſo diſpoſed as to the foreign Souldiers, the Duke of <hi>Guiſe calls to him, John Charron,</hi> Preſident of the Court of Revenues, (who, after a long canvaſing, and often repulſes, was at laſt put into that Office in the place of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus Provoſt of the Merchants), and commands him that he ſhould give notice to the Corporals <hi>to command their Souldiers to their Arms,</hi> but that they ſhould remain at the Town-Hall till midnight, there to underſtand what was needful to be done.</p>
            <p>The ſame thing was given in <hi>command to Marcellus,</hi> who though he was diſcharged of his office, yet for ſome private good offices that he had done, was retained in the Queens fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and kept his authority, though he loſt his dignity. He by often going to the Court, brought himſelf into an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with men, that he was in favour with the King and Queen; and upon that account was acceptable to the people, and from his mouth the people, that were of themſelves apt enough to ſtirs, were certified, <q>That it was the King's plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that they ſhould take Arms to cut off Coligny and the other Rebels; that therefore they ſhould ſee to it that none were ſpared, nor that thoſe wicked men ſhould be any where concealed. So the King will have it, ſo he commands, who alſo will provide that other Cities of the Kingdom do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently follow the example of the Pariſians. <hi>The ſign</hi> at which they ſhould riſe, is the tolling of the bell of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace-clock. <hi>The Mark</hi> whereby they ſhould be diſtinguiſhed from others, is white linen-cloath bound about their left arm, and a white croſs in their hats. That good ſtore of them ſhould therefore be ready with arms and good courage, and take care that candles be lighted in their windows throughout all their houſes: that no ſtir or tumult ariſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſign given.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The commands and admonitions of Marcellus are readily received by the Corporals, Colonels, Captains and Wardſmen of the City, who put themſelves into a poſture with the greateſt ſilence that the ſudden ſtate of things would permit; ſetting their Guards in the ſtreets and paſſages, but at firſt within dores. On the other part, the Duke of Guiſe and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goleſme
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151791:18"/>did what they could that things might be done as they were ordered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Queen fearing leſt the King,</hi> whom ſhe thought ſhe did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſtill wavering and ſtaggering at the horridneſs of the enterprize, <hi>ſhould change his mind, comes into his Bed chamber at midnight,</hi> whither preſently <hi>Anjou, Nevers, Biragus, Tavannes, Radeſianus,</hi> and after them <hi>Guiſe</hi> came by agreement. There they immind the King, heſitating, and after a long diſcourſe had to and fro, upbraided by his Mother, that by his delaying he would let ſlip a fair occaſion offered him by God, of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing his enemies. By which ſpeech<note n="*" place="margin">He died in leſs than two years after of a Bloudy-flux, proceeding, as was ſuſpected, from poiſon given him by the procurement of his Mother and Brother Anjou. <hi>v.</hi> l. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the King</hi> finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf accuſed of Cowardiſe, and being of himſelf of a fierce nature, and accuſtomed to bloud-ſhed, was inflamed, <hi>and gave command to put the thing in execution.</hi> Therefore <hi>the Queen</hi> laying hold of his preſent heat, leſt by delaying it ſhould ſlack, <hi>commands</hi> that the ſign which was to have been given at break of day ſhould be haſtened, and <hi>that the Bell</hi> of the nearer Church of St. German Auxerrois <hi>ſhould be tolled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. The Souldiers had for ſome time ſtood ready in their Arms drawn up in the ſtreets, expecting the ſign with greedy ears and deſires: by whoſe clattering and unuſual noiſe at ſo unſeaſonable a time, <hi>the Proteſtants</hi> who lodged by the King's command in the neighbouring lodgings, being <hi>awakened, went forth,</hi> and repaired toward the Louvre, where the concourſe was, and enquiring of thoſe they met what was the meaning of that concourſe of ſo many armed men, and why ſo many candles were lighted, they, as they were inſtructed (before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand) anſwered, that there was a certain mock-fight prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and that many from all parts did flock together to the ſight. But when notwithſtanding they went on further, they are <hi>injuriouſly repelled</hi> by the Guards that ſtood near the Caſtle, then railed upon, and reviled; laſtly, they were beaten; the firſt blow being given by a Gaſcoign, and one of them having received a blow, <hi>the reſt fell upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:151791:19"/>
            <p>Which <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">She lived to procure the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of all her Poſterity, and to ſee the death of all her ſons but <hi>Anjou,</hi> who ſurvived her but few months, being after a ſurious rebellion againſt him by Guiſe and this facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, murdered by a Fryer. Auguſt 24th.</note> 
               <hi>Queen</hi> underſtanding, being impatient of all delay, ſhe thence took occaſion to <hi>tell the King</hi> that the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers could not now be reſtrained, that he ſhould command the ſign from the Palace preſently to be given; for it was to be feared, that if it were delayed any longer, all would be in a confuſion, and things would fall out otherwiſe than he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. Therefore by his command <hi>the Bell of St. Germans</hi> Church <hi>is tolled</hi> before break of day ix Kal. VII br. which day is the Feaſt of St. Bartholomew, and fell upon a Sunday. And preſently <hi>Guiſe with Engoleſme and</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">He was ſlain in March fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, before Rochel. l <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aumale go to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligny's houſe,</hi> where Coſſerius kept Guard.</p>
            <p>Mean time <hi>Coligny</hi> being <hi>awakened,</hi> he underſtood by the noiſe that they were riſen into ſedition, yet being ſecure, and even ſure of the good will of the King, whether through his own credulity, or through the perſwaſion of his Son-in-law Teligny, he thus thought with himſelf; that the people were ſtirred up by the Guiſians, but as ſoon as they ſhould ſee the King's Guards under the command of Coſſenius for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of him and his, as he ſuppoſed, they would immediately fall off.</p>
            <p>But the tumult growing on, when he perceived a Gun diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged in the Court-yard of the houſe, then at laſt, but too late, <hi>conjecturing what the thing indeed was,</hi> he <hi>roſe</hi> from his bed, and putting on his night-gown, he raiſed himſelf upon his feet <hi>to his Prayers,</hi> leaning againſt the wall. La Bonne kept the keys of the houſe, who being commanded by Coſſenius, in the King's Name, to open the Gate, he ſuſpecting nothing, immediately opened it; ſtrait-way<note n="*" place="margin">He was ſlain <hi>18</hi> Apr. follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, before Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel, l. <hi>56.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Coſſenius going in,</hi> la Bonne meeting him, is ſtabbed with daggers; which, when the Switzers who were in the Court-yard ſaw, they fly into the houſe, and ſhutting after them the next gate of the houſe, they barracado it up with Cheſts, and Tables, and other houſhold-ſtuff, one only of the Switzers being ſlain in that firſt conflict by the Coſſenians, by a Muſquet diſcharged. At laſt the Gate being forced open, the Conſpirators ſtrive to get up the ſtairs. They were <hi>Coſſenius, Abinius, Corboran, Cardillac,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sarlaboun,</hi> chief officers of the Companies, <hi>Achilles, Petruccius</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151791:19"/>of Siena, all clad in Coats of Male, and <hi>Beſmes</hi> a German, educated from a child in the Family of Guiſe; for Guiſe himſelf, with the reſt of the Nobles and others, remained in the Court-yard. In that noiſe, after Prayers ended by Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin, the Miniſter <hi>Coligny,</hi> turning to thoſe who ſtood about him, who were for the moſt part Chirurgeons, and a few of his retinue. <q>I ſee, ſaith he, (with an undaunted counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance), what is doing; I am prepared patiently to undergo that death which I never feared, and which I have now long ſince embraced in my mind. Happy am I who ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my ſelf to die, and who ſhall die in God, by whoſe Grace I am raiſed to the hope of eternal life. Now I need not humane helps any longer. You, my friends, get ye hence with all the ſpeed that may be, leſt you be involved in my calamity, and your Wives hereafter wiſh evil to me being dead, as though I were the cauſe of your deaths. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, unto whoſe goodneſs I commend this ſoul which ſhall ſhortly fly from my body, is abundantly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</q> Which as ſoon as he had ſaid, they go into an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per room, and thence through the roof every one his way.</p>
            <p>Mean while the Conſpirators, breaking open the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores, ruſh in; and when as<note n="*" place="margin">He was killed about two years after, l. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Beſmes,</hi> with his ſword drawn, asked of Coligny who who ſtood by the dore, Art thou Coligny? He, with an undiſturbed countenance, anſwered, I am he: but, young man, reverence my gray hairs; whatſoever thou doeſt, thou canſt not make my life (much) ſhorter. Whiles he ſaid ſo, <hi>Beſmes thruſt his ſword into his breaſt,</hi> and drawing it forth, ſtruck him with a back-blow over the face, whereby he quite disfigured him: then with repeated blows he fell down dead. Some write that theſe words, ſhewing his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, fell from Coligny as he was dying. If at leaſt I had died by the hand of a man, not of a ſcullion. But Atinius, one of the Aſſaſines, repeated it ſo as I have written, and adds, that he never ſaw man in ſo preſent a danger bear death with ſuch conſtancy.</p>
            <p>[<hi>Much otherwiſe did Guiſe bear the ſenſe of his leſs apparent approaching death. For when after his conſpiracy and rebellion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151791:20"/>in the H. League againſt the next King, he was with ſuch like arts as had been here uſed, brought into the ſnare which the King had laid for him, and having before neglected the warnings of his friends, at laſt began to be ſuſpitious of his danger, though nothing viſible appeared his vehement fear ſo prevailed over his diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, whereby be endeavoured to conceal it, that his whole body, though he ſate by the fire, ſhaked and trembled, and, to immind him of this preſent fact, a ſtream of bloud flowing plentifully from his noſtrils; as he called for a napkin, he was fain to call for ſome Cordials to comfort his ſpirits: but yet nothing of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger viſible, when in the midſt of this his fear and languiſhing, he was by one of the Secretaries, who knew nothing of the deſign, called into the Kings Privy Chamber, whereupon, having ſaluted each of the company, as if he took his laſt farewell of them, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directly thither, he was no ſooner entred, but the dore was boulted, and one of thoſe who were appointed for the buſineſs, ſtruck a dagger through his throat downward into his breaſt, whereby his mouth was preſently filled with bloud, and ſtopped, that he could not ſpeak, but only fetch ſo deep a groan as was heard with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror by thoſe who ſtood by. This ſtroke was ſeconded by many others upon his head, breaſt, belly and groyn. And to this end he came, not as Colinius from his Prayers, but, after all his other wickedneſs, from his whore, with whom he had indulged the night, and therefore came later than the reſt this morning into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. Thu. l. <hi>93.</hi> It was their different lives and actions which made this difference in their deaths; for otherwiſe Guiſe was a man of great courage as well as Colinius.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Then Guiſe asking Beſmes out of the Court-yard, whether the thing were done? when he anſwered, it was done, he could not perſwade Angoleſme unleſs he ſaw it. Therefore Guiſe replying, and bidding him throw down the body, it was thrown out of the window into the Court-yard, as it was all beſmeared with bloud; when<note n="*" place="margin">He was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſtabbed to death. l. <hi>85.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Angoleſme</hi> not believing his own eyes, wiped off the bloud from his face with his handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and at laſt perceiving it was he, and as ſome add, kick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the corps in ſcorn, going out of the houſe with his fellows into the way; Go to, fellow Souldiers, ſaith he, let us proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute what we have ſo happily begun; for ſo the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151791:20"/>which words being often repeated, when forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>the Bell of the Palace clock rang</hi> out; they every where cryed, Arm, arm, and the people preſently ran to Coligny's houſe; then the carkaſs after it had been abuſed in a ſtrange manner, is caſt into the next Stable, and at laſt cutting off his head, (which was ſent as far as Rome), and his privy-members, and his hands, and his feet, they dragged it about the ſtreets to the bank of Siene; which thing he had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſaged by an ominous word, though he thought no ſuch thing. When he was about to be thrown into the River by the boys, from thence he was drawn to the Gibbet of Mount Faucon, where, with his legs upward, and his body down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, he is hanged in iron-chains: then a fire is made under him, by which he is only ſcorched, not conſumed; that he might as it were be tormented through all the Elements, ſlain upon the earth, drowned in the water, burnt in the fire, and hanged in the air. There when (his corps) had been expoſed for ſome days to the luſt and rage of all ſpectators, and to the juſt indignation of many, who did boad that that rage would hereafter coſt the King and all France dearly, Francis Momorancy, who had timely withdrawn himſelf from the danger, being near of kin, and nearer by friendſhip to the dead, took care that he ſhould by ſome truſty men be taken down by night, and committed to the earth in a Chapel at Chantilly.</p>
            <p>In Coligny's houſe were ſlain in the tumult whoſoever they met, or found hiding themſelves; and then the Souldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to plunder, and breaking open Cheſts, they take away mony, and other precious things, only they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve letters and papers, for ſo the Queen commanded.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Thence <hi>Nevers,</hi> and <hi>Tavannes,</hi> and <hi>Monpenſer,</hi> (who joyned himſelf to them, through the hatred that he bore to Proteſtants) <hi>ride armed through the City, and ſpurred on the people</hi> that ran already, telling them, <q>That Coligny and his Aſſociates had laid a plot againſt the King, the Queen, the King's Brethren, and Navar himſelf, and that it was detected by the ſingular Grace of God, and that the King prevented
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151791:21"/>them only in time: therefore, that they ſhould not ſpare the bloud of thoſe wicked men, who are the capital enemies of the King and Country, but that they ſhould fly upon their goods as ſpoil lawfully gotten; that it was the King's plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that that peſtiferous ſerpentine ſeed ſhould be extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the poiſon of hereſy being extinguiſhed, there ſhould for the future not ſo much as a word be ſpoken of any Religion but that of their fore-Fathers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then all being let looſe to ſatisfy their hatreds, every one proſecuted his enemy and rival with embittered minds. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brake into houſes through deſire of prey; all ran upon the ſlaughter without diſtinction. At the ſame time <hi>Francis Count de la Roche-fou cault,</hi> being for his facetiouſneſs and pleaſantneſs in diſcourſe very gracious with the King, when as but the day before he had, though unſeaſonably, drawn out the night till late in jeſting with the King, and from thence betook himſelf to his own houſe, he underwent the ſame fate with Coligny. For <hi>Bargius Avernus</hi> knocks at Roche-fou-cault's houſe, and telling him he had ſomething to acquaint him with from the King; Roche-fou-cault himſelf comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the dores to be unlocked, he is admitted in; when he ſaw men, as he thought, in diſguiſes, ſuppoſing the King was not far off, who had ſent men in jeſt to beat him, he beggeth them that they would deal better with him: but miſerable man, he found that the thing was not to be acted in jeſt, but in earneſt; when his houſe being plundered before his eyes, he himſelf half naked, was moſt cruelly butchered by one that ſtood by him.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Teligny</hi> the ſon-in-law of Coligny having, by running over the tops of houſes, eſcaped the hands of many, and at laſt being eſpied by the Guards of Anjou, he is alſo ſlain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonius Claromonlius Marqueſs of Revel,</hi> Brother, by the Mother, to Prince Porcian, who had a conteſt with <hi>Ludovicus Claromonlius Buſſius</hi> of Ambois, concerning the Marqueſat of Revel, came to Paris in the company of Navar, hoping there to put an end to his troubleſome controverſy. But the matter had a quite other end than he expected: for when
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151791:21"/>in that tumult he fled into the houſe that was next to his, at length he fell into the hands of his Couſin-German, purſuing him, who being his enemy upon no other account but the matter in controverſy, cruelly ſlew him. But not long after the controverſy being brought to an hearing, ſentence was given for Buſſius, but with no more happy ſucceſs: for by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an Edict afterwards made in favour of the Proteſtants, the ſentence was repealed, and Ludovicus himſelf was for a far different cauſe, with the ſame cruelty beheaded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonius Marafinus Guerchius</hi> a ſtout man, who the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had asked Coligny that he might lodge in his houſe, when, being in diſtreſs, he had not time to hide himſelf, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Cloak upon his arm, and drawing his ſword, he for a long time defended himſelf againſt the Aſſaſines; yet he ſlew none of them, being all in Coats of Male, but at laſt was overpowred by the multitude.</p>
            <p>The ſame calamity involved <hi>Baudineus,</hi> (the Brother of Acierius) <hi>Pluvialius, Bernius,</hi> being cruelly ſlain by the King's Souldiers: as alſo <hi>Carolus Quellevetus</hi> Pontius, Preſident of Armorica, who had married Katharina Parthenaea, daughter and heir of John Subizius: but the Mother of Parthenaea complaining of the frigidity of her ſon-in-law, a Suit had been commenced to diſſolve the Marriage, but was not yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. Therefore, when the bodies of the ſlain were thrown down as they were ſlain before the Palace, and in the ſight of the King and Queen, and all the Court-retinue, many Court-Ladies not being affrighted at the horridneſs of ſuch a ſpectacle, did with curious eyes ſhamefully behold the naked bodies, and eſpecially fixing their eyes on Pontius, did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine if they could by any means diſcover the ſigns of his frigidity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carolus Bellomanerius Lavardinus,</hi> the Kinſman of Pontius, and ſometime Tutor to the King of Navar in his childhood, fell into the hands of Petrus Lupus Preſident of the Court, a good man, who when he would have ſaved him, and was commanded by the Emiſſaries of the Court to diſpatch his priſoner; he, as he was a man of a ready and pleaſant wit, asked ſo much time as till he could raiſe his paſſion; by which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151791:22"/>ſpeech he for ſome time eluded their cruelty; but by and by a Meſſenger coming from the Palace as from the King, he was forced to deliver him into the hands of the Guard, who were to carry him before the King; but they in the way firſt ſtabbed Lavardinus with daggers, and then threw him over the Mill bridge into the River.</p>
            <p>The ſame fortune, and in the ſame place, ran <hi>Claudius Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimelus,</hi> an excellent Muſitian in our Age: who ſet the Pſalms of David, as they were put into verſe in the Mother-tongue by Clemens Marot, and Theodoret Beza, to divers pleaſant tunes, as they are now ſung in the publick and private meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Briolius</hi> a Gentleman who was Tutor to Marqueſs Conte in his childhood, venerable for his grey-head, being now an old man, was likewiſe ſlain in the embraces of his Pupil, who ſtretched forth his arms, and oppoſed his own body to the blows.</p>
            <p>Truly lamentable was the ſpectacle of <hi>Franciſcus Nompar Caumonlius:</hi> who had lodged in that neighbourhood, but which fortune, ſporting after her manner, mingled with an event of unexpected joyfulneſs: he with his two ſons whom he loved with a paternal affection, being taken in bed by the murderers, who proſecuted him with his children, not through an hatred of his Religion, but through hope of gain, was ſlain with one of his ſons: the other being all bloudy with the bloud that flowed upon him, ſaving himſelf from their blows, as he could at that tender age, (for he was hardly twelve years old), by the interpoſition of the dead bodies, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling himſelf dead, he was at laſt left by them for dead: a little after, more ran flocking to the houſe for prey, of whom ſome commended the fact, as well done; (for not only wild beaſts, but their whelps are altogether to be deſtroyed); others that had more humanity, ſaid, this might be lawful to be done upon the Father as guilty, but the innocent off ſpring, which perhaps would never take the ſame courſes, ought to be ſpared. Among thoſe that came toward the evening of that day, when as one did highly deteſt the fact, and ſaid God would be the avenger of ſuch impiety; the boy ſtretching his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151791:22"/>limbs, and a little liſting up his head, gave ſigns that he was alive: and when he asked him who he was, he anſwered not unadviſedly, that he was the Son and Brother of the ſlain, not telling his name; concerning which, when he was asked again, he anſwered that he would tell his name, if he would lead him where he deſired: and withal, asked him that he would take care to conduct him to the King's Armory, for he was near of kin to Biron Maſter of the Ordnance or Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery: nor ſhould he loſe his reward for ſo great a benefit: which thing he carefully performed. This <hi>James Nompar,</hi> that is his name, with great gratitude rewarded the man brought to him by the Divine Providence, and afterwards married the Daughter of Biron, and is now chief of a Noble Family in Aquitania, Godfry Caumont his Unckle being dead, and leaving only one Daughter. Being raiſed by the King to great honours, of which he carried himſelf worthy, as Colonel of the King's Life-guard, and Governour of Bearne, he ſeems to be preſerved from that danger by the ſingular Grace of God, that he might by his numerous off ſpring which he had by his Wife, propagate that Family that was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a few, and by his virtue add the higheſt ornament to the honours of his Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>The ſame day were ſlain theſe Proteſtants of great note, <hi>Loverius</hi> thrown out of a window into the high-way, <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamarius, Montalbertus, Roboreus, Joachinus, Vaſſorius, Cune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Rupius, Cobombarius, Velavaurius, Gervaſius, Barberius, Francurius,</hi> Chancellor to the King of Navar, <hi>Hieronimus Grolotius</hi> Governour of Aurleance, and <hi>Caliſtus</hi> his baſe Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who were both inhumanely dragged about the ſtreets, and at laſt caſt into the River, by the inſtigation of thoſe who gaped after his office and goods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stephanus Cevalerius Pruneus,</hi> the King's Treaſurer in Poictou, a man of great integrity, and one that was very ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous for the good of the Common-weal, who had been the principal mover for the building the Stone-bridge of Vienne, laid at Eraldi-caſtrum, was by certain cut-throats ſent by <hi>Stephanus Fergo Petauderius,</hi> (who ſought after his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer-ſhip), after the payment of a great ſum of mony, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151791:23"/>murdered, and thrown into the River, and Patanderius is, by the commendation of Monpenſerius, whoſe affairs he managed, put into his office.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Dionyſius Perrotus</hi> the Son of Aemilius, Senator of Paris, (a man not leſs renowned for his integrity than his knowledge in law), worthy of ſuch a Father, underwent the ſame fortune.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Nor did they ſpare <hi>thoſe whom Navar</hi> (being adviſed ſo to do by the King) <hi>had brought into the Palace:</hi> for they were by the King's command made to come down from their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters chambers into the Court-yard, and being brought out of the Palace, their ſwords being taken from them, they were many of them preſently ſlain at the Gate; others were hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the ſlaughter without the Palace. Among theſe were <hi>Pardallanius, Sammartinus, Burſius</hi> and <hi>Armannus, Claromon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Pilius,</hi> famous for his late valour in defending the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of St. John. He, when he was led out to be butchered, ſtanding before the heaps of the ſlain, is ſaid to cry out, <q>Is this the King's faith? Are theſe his promiſes? Is this the peace? But thou, O moſt great and moſt good God, behold the cauſe of the oppreſſed, and as a juſt Judge avenge this perfidy and cruelty:</q> and putting off his Coat which was very rich, gave it to a certain Gentleman of his acquaintance that ſtood by; Take this from me as a remembrance of my unworthy death: which gift he not accepting under that condition whiles Pilius ſaid theſe things, he was thruſt into the ſide with a ſpear, of which wound he fell down and died.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leiranus</hi> now grievouſly wounded, but eſcaping out of the hands of the murderers, ruſhing into the Queen of of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vars chamber, and hiding himſelf under her bed, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; and being carefully commended by Margaret to the King's Phyſitians, was healed. Bellonarius formerly Tutor to the King of Navar, having a long time lien under the Gout, was ſlain in his bed.</p>
            <p>The King received to his grace <hi>Grammontanus</hi> Lord of Gaſcoign, <hi>Johannes Durforlius Duralius, Joachimus Roaldus Gamarius,</hi> and <hi>Buchavarius,</hi> having promiſed to be faithful to him: and they were worth their word.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:151791:23"/>
            <p>Then <hi>the King calls Navar and Conde,</hi> and tells them, that from his youth, for many years, the publick peace had been diſturbed by often renewed wars, to the great damage of his affairs; but now, at laſt, by the grace of God, he had entred into ſuch a courſe as would extirpate all cauſes of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wars. That Coligny, the author of theſe troubles, was ſlain by his command, and that the ſame puniſhment was taken, throughout the City, upon thoſe wicked men who were infected with the poiſon of ſuperſtition: That he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred what great miſchiefs had befallen him from them, Navar and Conde, who had headed a company of profligate perſons, and ſeditiouſly raiſed war againſt him. That he had juſt reaſon to revenge theſe injuries, and now alſo had an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity put into his hand; but that he would pardon what was paſt upon the account of their conſanguinity, and the lately contracted affinity, and laſtly of their age: and that he would think that theſe things were not done by the advice or fault of them, but of Coligny and his followers, who had already, or ſhould ſhortly receive the juſt deſerts of their wickedneſs: that he was willing that thoſe things ſhould be buried in oblivion, provided they would make amends for their former offences, by their future loyalty and obedience; and renouncing their profane ſuperſtitious Doctrine, would return to the Religion of their Anceſtors, that is, to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Religion: for he would have only that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion profeſſed in his Kingdom which he had received from his fore-Fathers. Therefore, that they ſhould look to it that they do comply with him herein, otherwiſe they might know that the ſame puniſhment which others had ſuffered, did hang over their heads.</p>
            <p>To this the King of <hi>Navar</hi> did moſt humbly beg, that no violence might be offered to their conſciences nor perſons, and that then they would remain faithful to him, and were ready to ſatisfy him in all things. But <hi>Conde</hi> added, that he could not perſwade himſelf that the King, who had engaged himſelf by ſolemn oath to all the Proteſtant Princes of his Kingdom, would upon any account violate it, or hearken to their enemies and adverſaries in that matter. As to Religion,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151791:24"/>that was not to be commanded, that his life and fortunes were in the King's power to do with them what he pleaſed; but that he knew he was to give an account only to God of that Religion that he had received from God. Therefore that he was fixed and reſolved never to recede from his Religion, which he knew aſſuredly was true, no, not for any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent danger of life. With which anſwer the King being highly provoked, he called Conde ſtubborn, ſeditious, Rebel, and the ſon of a Rebel, and told him, that if he did not change his mind within three days, his head ſhould pay for his obſtinacy.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Many of the Proteſtant Nobles had taken up their lodgings in <hi>the Suburbs of St. German,</hi> and could not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to lie in the City. Among theſe were <hi>Johannes Roanus Frontenaeus, Godofridus Caumonlius, Vidame of Chartres, Gabriel Mongomerius, Jo. Lafinius, Bellovarius, Segurius Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dallanius,</hi> and others. The deſtroying of whom was given in charge to <hi>Laurentius Maugironus:</hi> and beſides Marcells was ordered to take care that 1000 Souldiers of the City Trained-Bands ſhould be ſent thither to Maugironus, who went but ſlowly on in his buſineſs.</p>
            <p>While this was doing, tidings came to <hi>Mongomery</hi> of the rumor of taking up Arms in the City, who ſignified the ſame to the <hi>Vidame of Chartres,</hi> and preſently they met all together, uncertain what was to be done; for that many confiding in the King's faithfulneſs, perſwaded themſelves that this was done without the King's command, by the Guiſians, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the forwardneſs of the ſeditious people, therefore they thought it was beſt to go to the King, and that he would ſuccour them againſt any violence.</p>
            <p>In that doubtfulneſs of mind (though the more prudent did not doubt that theſe things were done by agreement, and by the King's command) were many hours ſpent, ſo that they might eaſily have been deſtroyed, but that another impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment happened to the Conſpirators; for whiles Maugironus doth in vain expect Pariſians to be ſent from Guiſe, who were all buſied in plundering, Guiſe impatient of further delays, calls forth the King's Guards out of the Louvre, intending
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151791:24"/>whiles they paſſed the River to go thither himſelf. And when he came to the gates, it did too late appear that they had miſtaken the keys, therefore while they ſent for others, it being now broad day, the Switzers and others of the King's Guards paſſing the Siene, were ſeen from the other ſide: and upon the diſcharging of a Gun on the other ſide of the River, as was thought by the King's command, the Aſſociates take counſel to fly, and before they came, were gotten a good way off. Guiſe purſued Mongomery and others to Montfort, but in vain, and meeting with <hi>Sanleodegarius,</hi> he commands him that he ſhould follow them with freſh horſes. There were ſome ſent to Udencum, and to Dreux, who ſhould intercept them if they went that way: but all in vain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Franciſcus Bricomotius,</hi> who could not be deſtroyed in the tumult, flies to the Engliſh Ambaſſadors lodgings,<note n="†" place="margin">In Bernardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum caio.</note> where he for ſome days lay hid. <hi>Arnoldus Cavagnius</hi> alſo hid himſelf not far from hence, with a friend, who fearing the danger, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired him to provide for himſelf; but both being taken, were caſt into the Palace priſon, and with that event which we ſhall ſhew anon.</p>
            <p>In the mean time Guiſe, with Aumale and Angoleſme, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into the City, where the King's Guards did commit out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages upon the lives and fortunes of the Proteſtant Nobles and Gentlemen, even of thoſe that were their familiars, and well known to them. This work being aſſigned to them in particular, whiles the people incited by the Sheriffs wardſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and tything-men that ran about, did furiouſly rage with all manner of licentiouſneſs and exceſs againſt their fellow-Citizens, and <hi>a ſad and horrid face of things</hi> did every where appear. For the ſtreets and ways did reſound with the noiſe of thoſe that flocked to the ſlaughter and plunder, and the complaints and doleful out-cries of dying men, and thoſe that were nigh to danger were every where heard. The carkaſſes of the ſlain were thrown down from the windows, the Courts &amp; chambers of houſes were full of dead men, their dead bodies rolled in dirt were dragged through the ſtreets, bloud did flow in ſuch abundance through the chanels of the ſtreets, that full
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151791:25"/>
               <hi>ſtreams of bloud</hi> did run down into the River: the number of the ſlain, men, women, even thoſe that were great with child, and children alſo, was innumerable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Annas Terrerius Chapius,</hi> being eighty years old, and an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate of great name in the Senate, was ſlain. Alſo <hi>Jo. Lomerius Secretary</hi> to the King, having compounded for his ſafety, was thrown into Gaol by <hi>Johannes Pariſienſis</hi> Judge of Criminals, and having ſold<note n="*" place="margin">Verſalium fundum.</note> 
               <hi>his Eſtate at Verſailles</hi> to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, with whom he had a Suit depending about it, at a low rate, and leaving his office upon the account of another, was afterwards ſlain by the command of thoſe with whom he had thoſe dealings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magdalena Briſſonetta</hi> the Relict of Theobaldus Longiolius (an Iriſh-man, Maſter of the Requeſts) Neece of Cardinal Gulielmus Briſſonettus, and beſides, a woman of moſt rare accompliſhments, and of no mean learning, when in old ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, taking with her her daughter Franciſca, and Johannes Spina a noted Preacher, who was her houſhold Chaplain, ſhe would have fled out of the City, being diſcovered by the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throats, and in vain put to renounce her Religion, being thruſt into the body with pike-ſtaves, half dead, ſhe was tumbled from the Key into the River, where ſwimming about, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of boats being drawn together, as if it had been to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a mad dog, with many gentle blows, ſhe was at length moſt inhumanely drowned: <hi>Spina</hi> not being known, eſcaped in the throng, and CL. Marcellus coming in, they ſpared her daughter for her ages ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Ramus,</hi> who was born at Vermand, when he had for a long time taught good learning, Philoſophy, &amp; at laſt Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, in Prelaea Schola, of which he was Maſter, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the King's School, he at laſt brought erroneous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine into his Philoſophy, vehemently oppoſing Ariſtotle both by word and writing. When as there were great diſputes between him and <hi>Jacobus Carpentarius, Claromontanus,</hi> as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly there had been greater with Antonius Goveanus, and Joachinus Periomus; yet herein he was worthy of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that by his wit, diligence, aſſiduity and wealth, he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151791:25"/>did what in him lay to promote Learning, inſtituting a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematick Lecture, to which he gave out of his own Eſtate a yearly ſtipend of 300 pounds. He being drawn out of his Cell, wherein he had hid himſelf, by ſome murderers ſent by Carpentar, his Rival, who alſo promoted the ſedition, after he had payed (ſome) mony, receiving ſome wounds, was thrown out of a window into the yard, whereby his bowels guſhed out; which the boys, fet on by the fury of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged Maſters, threw about the ſtreets, and whipping his carkaſs with ſcourges in reproach to his profeſſion, dragged it about in a moſt ſhameful and cruel manner. Which thing, when it came to the hearing of <hi>Dionyſius Lambinus,</hi> Monſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienſis, King's profeſſor of humanity, and of both Languages, and who, by many books that he had publiſhed, deſerved well of Learning, and he was otherwiſe no friend to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctrine, yet was he ſo affrighted at the example of Ramus, that he could not be comforted, and it made ſo deep an impreſſion upon his mind, that he fell into a moſt grievous diſeaſe, of which about a month after he died.</p>
            <p>From their contentions the name of <hi>Politick</hi> took its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, which afterwards became a note of faction, being given by the ſeditious, by thoſe that favoured the King's par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the peace of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="21">21. This fury did extend it ſelf to <hi>thoſe that never profeſſed the Proteſtant Doctrine.</hi> For <hi>Gulielmus Bertrandus, Villemorius</hi> Maſter of Requeſts, (ſon of Jo. Bertrand Vice-Chancellor, and afterwards Cardinal) a good man, and liberal, and one that was injurious to none, was ſpoiled of his mony, and then ſlain by cut-throats ſent by the above-mentioned Fergo.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Jacobus Poliardus,</hi> a Senator of Paris, and Fellow of the Sacred Colledge, otherwiſe an unquiet and quarrelſome man, and one that was troubleſome to the Pariſian Captains, when he had for ſome days lien hid in the houſe of a Prieſt, his Friend, being diſcovered by the pratling of a Girl, was at length delivered into the hands of the murderers, and by one <hi>Cruciarius,</hi> (that was his name), a Goldſmith, after he had for ſome time kept him between hope and fear, had his head cut off. I have often beheld and heard that man that very well
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151791:26"/>deſerved a Gallows, in a ſtrange kind of cruel madneſs boaſt, ſtretching forth his naked arm, that with this arm he had in that maſſacre ſlain above 400 men. Afterward, whether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to it by repentance, or the terror of his conſcience, he put on hair-cloath, and being infamous for ſo many murders, that he might avoid the ſight of men, he went into ſolitude, profeſſing the life of an Anchoret: where yet he could not forget his cruel nature: for in theſe late wars he was accuſed, and almoſt convicted, that by the help of ſuch men as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he had cut the throat of a Flemiſh Merchant, whoſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity compelled him to repair to his Cell.</p>
            <p>Laſtly <hi>Petrus Salſeda</hi> a Spaniard,<note n="†" place="margin">Vici in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diomatricibus praefectus.</note> who ſtirred up the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals war, of which we have ſpoken before, though he was no way enclined to the Proteſtant Doctrine, was the ſame day ſlain by thoſe who ſought to revenge a former injury.</p>
            <p>[<hi>One</hi> Ronlart <hi>a Catholick, and Canon of Noſtre Dame, and alſo a Counſellor in the Parliament uttering certain ſpeeches in miſliking this lawleſs kind of proceeding without juſtice, was apprehended, and committed to priſon, and murthered as diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly as any of the reſt, wherewith divers of the Catholicks them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were offended. This manner of proceeding breedeth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral miſtruſt in them of the Nobility, and every man feareth God's vengeance.</hi> Walſingham, Let. 16. Sept. 1572. In the Compleat Ambaſſador, p. 246.]</p>
            <p>And many of the Nobles <hi>eſcaped</hi> with great danger, and eſpecially <hi>Thoreus,</hi> who warned Coligny when Coſſenius was deſigned to guard him, that he could not be committed to a more deadly enemy; and that now it was true that the ſheep was committed to the woolf. But it was believed that upon the account of the abſence of his Brother Momorancy, he and his Brethren <hi>Damvilla</hi> and <hi>Mernvius</hi> were ſpared. <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaeus</hi> his life was alſo in danger, for that he joyned with the Momorancies, and favoured not the Guiſians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bironus</hi> in the Armory fearing upon the ſame account what would become of him, planting two Culverins againſt the City, fortified himſelf till the ſury of the people and the guards ceaſed.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151791:26"/>
            <p>Among the Proteſtants that were of any note, there eſcaped by a rare kindneſs of fortune, <hi>Joh. Sancomonlius, Sauromarius Cugius Bricomolius Junior,</hi> and ſome few others, <hi>Jacobus Cruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolius Acierius,</hi> by the commendation of his Brother Antony<note n="†" place="margin">Uticenſium ducis.</note> Duke of Uzes, and command of the Queen, with ſome others of the Nobility, were preſerved by the Guiſians to this intent, as it was reported; that they might caſt the odium of the Maſſacre upon the King and the fury of the people; as though they had no other deſign than to revenge their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate injuries upon the head of Coligny, and alſo that they might by ſuch a benefit hold thoſe whom they preſerved ever obliged to them. Nor did their expectations fail them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gulielmus Altamarus Fervacius</hi> did endeavour to procure the ſame favour from the King for <hi>Franciſcus Moninius,</hi> but all in vain; but he being diſcovered by his means, ſtrait-way it was given in command to Marcellus to cut him off by the cut-throats. <hi>That day</hi> were <hi>ſlain</hi> to the number of <hi>two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Toward the evening <hi>Proclamation</hi> was <hi>made</hi> to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude by ſound of Trumpet, that every one ſhould betake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his own home, nor might any ſtir abroad; that only the King's Guards, and the Officers with their Troops of Horſe, ſhould go about the City upon pain of death to them that did not obey: ſo that when it was thought that there was an end put to thoſe ſlaughters and rapines, the ſame maſſacre and liberty of plundering was continued the night following, and the days following.</p>
            <p n="22">22. The ſame day <hi>the King,</hi> whether troubled at the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridneſs, or fearing the odium of the fact, <hi>by Letters</hi> directed to the Governors of the Provinces, <hi>caſteth the odium upon the Guiſians,</hi> telling them <q>That the ſedition was raiſed without his privity or conſent: that they, as ſoon as they perceived that the friends and kindred of Coligny, whom he ſtill cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led couſin, did intend to revenge the wound given him, that they might be before-hand with them, ſtirred up ſo great a party of the Nobles and Pariſians, that they, by their help, cut off the Guards that he had aſſigned to Coligny, and as many of his friends as they met: and this example was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151791:27"/>with ſuch fury and violence throughout the City, that ſuch a remedy as might be wiſhed, could not be applied in any due time. Now at laſt the ſedition that ſeemed to be allayed, was again upon old grudges between the two Families, revived; which thing, ſince it hapned contrary to his will, he would that all ſhould underſtand that the Edict lately publiſhed, was not thereby in any part violated: but he did command that it ſhould be religiouſly obſerved, and that the Governors ſhould ſee to it, that mutual ſlaughters ſhould not be committed in other Cities, nor that they ſhould take Arms one againſt another, but that every one ſhould keep home in the City and Countrey, and abſtain from violence upon pain of death to thoſe that did not obey.</q> In the end of the Letter theſe words were added; <q>Here I am with my Brother of Navar, and my Couſin Conde, ready to undergo the ſame fortune with them.</q> The ſame day were <hi>Letters of the ſame contents written by the Queen,</hi> ſent not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the Kingdom, but to the Dyet or Aſſembly of Switzers, and diſperſed by the King's command through England, and divers places in Germany.</p>
            <p n="23">23. The next day ſlaughters and rapines were continued. <hi>Petrus Platius</hi> Preſident of the Court of Cuſtoms, a man eminent for his gravity, learning and integrity, (whom one Michael by name, Captain of a Band, had the day before cheated of a great ſum of Gold) by the help of ſlingers lent to him by Nic. Bellofremontius Seneſcaeus, and Carronius Provoſt of the Merchants, defended himſelf from the fury of the people. That <hi>Seneſcaeus</hi> was lately by the King put into the place of Innocentius Triperius Monſtrolius, great Provoſt del' Hoſpital: under whom that Office, whoſe juriſdiction belonged only to ſome mean perſon of the King's Retinue, after that began to be conferred upon Gentlemen, as all thoſe things which belong to the Maſter and Colonels of the Horſe. He firſt obtained the name of great Provoſt, thoſe being much offended at it, who, by how much was added to him in titles did complain that by ſo much their juriſdiction was diminiſhed. That ſo large juriſdiction for ſome time after the death of Monſtrolius had ceaſed, which at laſt the King
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151791:27"/>conferred upon Seneſcaeus, for the Nobleneſs of his Family, and ſuch learning as with us is rare in a military perſon. Therefore Seneſcaeus coming this day from the King to Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, told him that though the King reſolved utterly to root out the Proteſtants by flaying them, that there ſhould not remain one that piſſeth againſt the wall, yet that for many reaſons he would give him his life, and ſent him to conduct him to the Louvre, for that he did deſire to learn from him many things concerning the affairs of the Proteſtants, which it behoved him to know. Then Placius deſired to excuſe himſelf, and deſired that he might ſtay till the fury of the people were ſomewhat allayed; that in the mean time he might be kept priſoner whereſoever it pleaſed the King. On the other ſide Seneſcaeus, who had received ſuch command from the Queen, did haſten him, that he ſhould without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay obey the King's command, and aſſigned him Pezovius, one of the privy leaders of the Sedition, for his greater ſecurity as he ſaid: by whom he was delivered into the hands of thoſe that lay in wait, and being thrown off his Mule upon which he rode, he was ſtabbed with daggers: his body was dragged, and thrown into the ſtable of a publick houſe; and his houſe lay three days open to ranſacking, his wife being fled, and his children wandring hither and thither. His office, which in his abſence, in the time of war was managed by <hi>Stephanus Nuellius,</hi> a factious and bloud-thirſty man, and who was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to have hired theſe cut-throats againſt the life of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, was by him obtained of the King.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Such cruelty raging every where, while the Heavens ſeemed more than ordinarily ſerene, an accident hapned whereby the minds of the enraged people were after a ſtrange manner inflamed. An Oxyacantha, which is a kind of ſhrub which they call <hi>white-thorn,</hi> growing in the Church-yard of St. Innocents, did, whether of its own accord, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times happens, when nature failing, that plant is come to that, that it is about to dry up; or whether by warm water poured upon it by impoſtors, did in an unuſual time <hi>put forth its flower.</hi> All which, the factions flattering themſelves in their madneſs, did refer to God, ſignifying by theſe tokens,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151791:28"/>that what they had done was acceptable to him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſaid, that the Heavens did rejoyce to ſee the Maſſacre of the Proteſtants. And James Carpenter alluding to the Month, in a writing that he publiſhed, called that light <hi>Auguſta.</hi> Therefore the ſeditious flocking together at the fame of the bloſſoming thorn, did skip about with great joy: which they alſo teſtified by the unuſual beating of a Drum, though without command, (for even that they might do then) and ſo interpreted it, as if the Proteſtants being rooted out, the Catholick Religion, and the Kingdom of France ſhould recover its ancient ſplendor and flower. But the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants argued otherwiſe; and if this were to be looked upon as a Miracle, they ſaid this was portended by this ſign; that though the Church might ſeem by this wound to be utterly extinct, yet it ſhould come to paſs that it ſhould in a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and incomprehenſible manner revive and flouriſh; which alſo they did confirm by the example of the wonder ſhewed to Moſes in the buſh, which, though it burned, yet was it not conſumed. They added, that it might be ſaid rather to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the commendation of innocence, than the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of butchery, becauſe the thorn bloſſomed in a place which took its name from Innocents.</p>
            <p>The ſame day ſome drawn out of the King's Life-Guard by Gaſpar Caſtreus Nancaeus, are by the King's command ſent to<note n="†" place="margin">Caſtillionem ad Lupam.</note> Chaſtillon, to take and bring <hi>Coligny's wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> as alſo the ſons of Andoletus. But Franciſcus the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son of Coligny, and Vidus Lavallus the Eldeſt Son of Andoletus, had already faved themſelves by flight. All the reſt are taken, and brought with all their precious houſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuff to Paris.</p>
            <p n="25">25. It was <hi>the King's deſign,</hi> that as ſoon as the ſlaughter of Coligny and his followers had been performed, the Guiſes ſhould immediately depart the City, and go every one to his own houſe, that thereby all might take notice, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever had been done at Paris proceeded from their faction. But the Queen and Anjou eſpecially (who did both of them with an over-weaning affection incline to the party of Guiſe) did intercede: (ſeeing) the King was at firſt enraged only
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151791:28"/>againſt Coligny, as not yet forgetting his flight from Meaux, drew him on, who yet wavered, to the ſlaughter of all the Proteſtants in the City; ſo that not knowing where he ſet his foot, they brought him by degrees to this paſs, that he ſhould take the whole blame upon himſelf, and ſo caſe the Guiſians, who were not able to bear ſuch a burden. And to that end Anjou did, as it it was laid, produce Letters found in Teligny's desk, written by the hand of Momorancy, in which, after the wound given to Coligny, he did affirm that he would revenge this injury upon the Authors of it, who were not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known with the ſame mind as if it had been offered to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>Thereupon the Queen and Anjou took occaſion to ſhew the King, <q>That if he perſiſted in his former diſſimulation, things were come to that paſs, that he would endanger the ſecurity of the Kingdom, his Fortunes, Riches, and Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. For the Guiſians, who do by theſe Letters, and otherwiſe, underſtand the mind of the Momorancies, being men deſirous of troubles, and ſeeking grounds of them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every occaſion, will never lay down their Arms which they have by the King's command taken up, to offer this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury: that they will ſtill keep them under pretence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſending their ſafety, which they ſay is aimed at by the enemy; and ſo that which was thought to have been the end of a moſt bloudy war, will prove to be the beginning of a more dangerous one. For the remainders of the Proteſtants, who ſee their matters diſtreſſed, will, without doubt, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther themſelves to the Momorancies, who are of themſelves ſtrong and thence will take new ſtrength and ſpirits: which if it ſhould happen, what a face of the Kingdom will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, when the name and authority of the King's Majeſty being ſlighted and trampled upon, every one ſhall take liberty to himſelf, and indulge to private hatred and affections accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t? Laſtly, what will foreign Princes think of the King, who ſuffers himſelf to be over-ruled by his ſubject, who cannot keep his ſubjects in their duty, and laſtly, who knows not how to hold the reins of legal power?
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151791:29"/>Therefore there is no other way to prevent ſo great an evil, but for the King to approve by his publick Proclamation, of what was done, as if it had been done by his command. For by this means he ſhould take the arbitrement and power to himſelf; and on the one hand diſarm the Guiſes, and on the other hand keep the Momorancies from taking up Arms; and laſtly ſhould bring it about, that the Proteſtant affairs now already very low, ſhould be ſeparated from the cauſe of the Momorancies. That the King ought not to fear the odium of the thing: for there is not ſo much danger in the horridneſs of a fact, (the odium whereof may be ſomewhat allayed by excuſe), as in the confeſſion of weakneſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, which doth neceſſarily bring along with it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, which is almoſt deſtructive to Princes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe reaſons they eaſily perſwaded an imperious Prince, who leſs feared hatred than contempt, that he might recall the Guiſians to obedience, and retain the Momorancies in their loyalty, to confirm by publick teſtimony, that whatſoever had been done, was done by his will and command. Therefore in the morning, viz. upon the Tueſday, he <hi>came into the Senate</hi> with his Brethren, the King of Navar, and a great retinue of Nobles, after they had heard Maſs with great ſolemnity, and ſitting down in the Chair of State, all the orders of the Court being called together, <q>He complained of the grievous injuries that he had from a child received from Gaſpar Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligny, and wicked men falſly pretending the name of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: but that he had forgiven them by Edicts made for the publick Peace. That Coligny, that he might leave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be added to his wickedneſs, had entred into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy how to take away him, his mother, his brethren, and the King of Navar himſelf, though of his own Religion, that he might make young Conde King, whom he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined afterwards to ſlay likewiſe, that the Royal Family being extinct, he uſurping the Kingdom, might make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf King. That he, when it could not otherwiſe be, did, though full ſore againſt his will, extinguiſh one miſchief by another, and as in extream dangers, did uſe extream reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151791:29"/>that he might extirpate that impure contagion out of the bowels of the Kingdom. Therefore, that all ſhould take notice, that whatſoever had been that day done by way of puniſhment upon thoſe perſons, had been done by his ſpecial command.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After he had ſaid theſe things, <hi>Chriſtophorus Thuanus,</hi> chief Preſident, in a ſpeech fitted to the time, commended the King's prudence, who, by diſſembling ſo many injuries, had timely prevented the wicked conſpiracy, and the danger that was threatned by it, and that that being ſuppreſſed, he had now ſetled peace in the Kingdom, having well learnt that ſaying of Lewis XI. He that knows not how to diſſemble, knows not how to reign.</p>
            <p>Then the Court was commanded that diligent enquiry ſhould be made concerning the conſpiracy of Coligny and his Aſſociates, and that they ſhould give ſentence according to form of Law, as the heinouſneſs of the fact did require. Then laſtly <hi>Vidus Faber Pibraccius,</hi> Advocate of the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (or Attorney-General) ſtood up, and asked the King whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did will and command that this declaration ſhould be entred into the acts of the Court, to the preſervation of the memory of it? whether the orders of Judges and Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, which he had complained were corrupted, ſhould be reformed? And laſtly, whether by his command there ſhould be an end put to the ſlaughters and rapines? To theſe things the King anſwered, that he did command the firſt; that he would take care about the ſecond, and that for the third he did give command by publick proclamation through all the ſtreets of the City, that they ſhould for the future ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from all ſlaughters and rapines. Which declaration of the King aſtoniſhed many, and among the reſt <hi>Thuanus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who was a man of a merciful nature, and altogether averſe from bloud, and feared that example, and the danger that was threatned thereby: who alſo did with great freedom privately reprove the King, for that, if the conſpiracy of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligny and his company had been true, he did not rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt them by Law. This is moſt certain, he did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151791:30"/>deteſt St. Bartholomews-day, uſing thoſe verſes of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Papinius in a different caſe,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Excidat illa dies aevo, nec poſtera credaut</l>
               <l>Saecula, nos certe taceamus, &amp; obruta multa</l>
               <l>Nocte, tegi propriae patiamur crimina Gentis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So that he ſeems to have commended the King's art by a ſpeech fitted to the preſent time and place, rather than from his heart.</p>
            <p>The adviſing of the King to enquire into this conſpiracy, is thought to have been from <hi>James Morvillerius</hi> Biſhop of Orleans, who had left his Biſhoprick to give himſelf wholly to the Court: a man of a cautious nature, but moderate and juſt, and who was never the author of that bloudy counſel. But when as that which was done could not be undone, he thought it was beſt for the reputation of the King, and for the publick Peace, that ſince the odium of it could not be wholly aboliſhed, yet that it might by ſome means be mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he perſwaded the King and Queen, that to the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now done, they ſhould, though in a prepoſterous manner, apply the authority of Law; and that proof being made of the conſpiracy, judgment ſhould be paſſed upon the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in form of Law; which thing Thuanus himſelf appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, being conſulted about it by Morvillerius upon the King's command.</p>
            <p>Two days after <hi>a Jubilee</hi> is appointed, and Prayers are made by the King, and a full Court in a great aſſembly of people, and thanks were returned to God, for that things had ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſo happily, and according to their deſires. And the ſame day <hi>an Edict</hi> was <hi>publiſhed,</hi> wherein the King declared, that <q>Whatſoever had happened in this matter was done by his expreſs command; not through hatred of (their) Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or that it ſhould derogate from the Edicts of Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which he would have to ſtand ſtill in force, and to be religiouſly obſerved, but that he might prevent the wicked conſpiracy of Coligny and his confederates. Therefore,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151791:30"/>that he did will and command that all Proteſtants ſhould live at home quietly and ſecurely under his protection and patronage, and did command all his Governors to take di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent care that no violence or injury ſhould be offered to them,</q> either in their lives, goods or fortunes; adding a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that whoſoever did otherwiſe, ſhould underſtand that he did it under pain of life. To theſe things a clauſe was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally added, which the Proteſtants did interpret to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict what he had ſaid before; that, <q>Whereas upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their meetings, and publick Aſſemblies, great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and grievous offences had been ſtirred up, they ſhould for the future abſtain from ſuch meetings, whether publick or private, upon what pretence ſoever, till further order was taken by the King, upon pain of life and fortunes to thoſe that diſobeyed.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26. Theſe Edicts and Mandates were diverſly entertained <hi>in the Provinces,</hi> according to the divers natures and factions of the Governors; for thoſe that were addicted to the party of the Momorancies, made a moderate uſe of them, but great was the rage and fury of others to whom ſecret com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands were brought, not in writing, but by Emiſſaries, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the example of the Pariſian Maſſacre.</p>
            <p>The beginning was <hi>at Meaux,</hi> as being neareſt, where the ſame day that the Maſſacre had been at Paris, above two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred were thrown into priſon by <hi>Coſſetus</hi> Advocate of the Treaſury, an impudent man, who was chiefly aſſiſted by <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius Rollandus</hi> an Apparitor, and <hi>Columbus</hi> a Mariner. The next day they ſet upon the Market that is out of the City, and the men being ſlipt away, they fell upon the women, whereof 25 were ſlain, and ſome of them violated by the rude mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers. The day following, after they had every where rifled the houſes of the ſuſpected, they come to thoſe that were impriſoned, who being called out one by one by Coſſetus himſelf, were there ſlain as Oxen, by Butchers, in a Slaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and thrown into the Caſtle-ditch, and the greateſt part of them (the cut-throats being wearied) were drowned in the River Marne. And then Coſſetus exhorts the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places that they ſhould proceed in what had been ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151791:31"/>begun. But the preſence of Momorancy Preſident of l'Iſle la France, who was then at Cantilia, not far from thence, did hinder the ſeditious from ſtirring at Senlis.</p>
            <p>But great was the rage at <hi>Orleans,</hi> which being once or twice taken by the Proteſtants, the ſad ruines of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed Churches lying open to the eyes of all, did enkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the minds of the people to revenge their injuries, being yet freſh: the day following therefore they began upon <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellus Bovillus,</hi> one of the King's Counſellors, whom being ignorant of what had happened at Paris, Curtius a Weaver, the leader of the ſeditious, with ſome of his party, went as it were to viſit in the evening; he thinking that they came as friends to ſup with him, entertained them as at a feaſt; which (entertainment) the murderers having received, they acquaint him with what was done at Paris, and withal demand his Purſe, which being delivered, they in the midſt of their entertainment ſlay their <hi>Hoſt.</hi> From thence, as if this had been the ſign given, they flock together for three days to murder and ſpoil; above 1000 men, women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as it was thought, were ſlain; part were caſt into the river Loire: thoſe that were ſlain without the City were thrown into the ditch. Great was the plunder that was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in all that time, and eſpecially the copious Library of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Montaureus</hi> (a learned man, who died four years ſince of grief of mind, at Sancerra) furniſhed with Books of all ſorts, eſpecially with mathematical Manuſcripts, the greateſt part of them Greek, and corrected and illuſtrated by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of Montaureus himſelf, as alſo with inſtruments uſeful in that Science, contrived with admirable artifice, was with a moſt barbarous outrage taken away.</p>
            <p>Alſo ſome were ſlain at <hi>Gergolium,</hi> the people raging through the neighbouring Cities, Towns and Villages, after the manner of the Inhabitants of Orleance.</p>
            <p>The ſame was done at <hi>Angiers,</hi> they beginning with <hi>Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Maſſonius Riverius,</hi> who was moſt barbarouſly ſlain as he walked in his Garden, by a cut-throat let in by his Wife, who ſuſpected no ſuch thing: as alſo others. <hi>Barbeus</hi> Enſign of the Prince of Conde's Regiment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the danger by flight,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151791:31"/>as alſo Renatus Roboreus Breſſaldus, one that was very trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to Prieſts, many of whom he had unworthily maimed, was after wards executed.</p>
            <p>The Townſmen of <hi>Troyes,</hi> of whom Coligny had a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before complained to the King, when they heard of the tumult at Paris, preſently ſet guards at the City-gates, that none might ſlip ſorth: and having upon 3 Kal. VII bris,<note place="margin">Auguſt 30th.</note> caſt all the ſuſpected into priſon five days after, by the command <hi>Anna Valdraeus Simphalius,</hi> Governor of Troyes, upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of <hi>Petrus Bellinus</hi> (who, as was believed, came lately from Paris with private commands) they were brought out one by one, and ſlaughtered by the cut-throats, and buried in a ditch digged in the very priſon: and preſently after, the King's Proclamation, wherein they were commanded to leave of killing and ſpoiling, was publiſhed by Simphalius, who, as it is ſaid, received it before the ſlaughter was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Vierzon,</hi> when as at the yet uncertain report of the news, the Gates of the City were ſhut up by the diverſity of Letters that were ſent in the King's Name, the Townſmen held their hands for ſome time from violence, contenting themſelves to have caſt the ſuſpected into priſon, till at laſt ſtirred up by the example of the men of Orleance, they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the ſame madneſs againſt the impriſoned. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus Hottomannus,</hi> and <hi>Hugo Donellus,</hi> who profeſſed Civil Law in that City, by the help of their Scholars, and eſpecially of the Germans, eſcaped the preſent danger.</p>
            <p>Two days after the uproar at Paris, the Regiment of Horſe that belonged to Ludovicus Gonzaga, under pretence of muſter, and receiving their pay, ſeized on <hi>la Charite,</hi> a Town lying upon the River Loire, below Nevers, and the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtirred up by Letters from Paris, 18 were ſlain in the Town; <hi>Petrus Mebelinus,</hi> and <hi>Johannes Lerius,</hi> well known by his voyage into America, did beyond their hopes eſcape the hands of the murderers, and fled to Sancerra.</p>
            <p n="27">27. The greateſt Maſſacre of all was at <hi>Lions,</hi> for in that City, as it is very populous, the Gates being preſently ſhut, many are taken and caſt into priſon, by the command of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151791:32"/>Mandelotus,</hi> Governor of the Town, under pretence, as he ſaid, that the King's Guards might protect them from the rage of the people: but many while they are lead by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, as if it had been to priſon, are ſlain in the blind lanes of the Town, and preſently caſt into the Rivers la Saone and Rhone. The ring-leader and chief promoter of this was one <hi>Boidonus,</hi> a wicked debauched fellow, who afterward came to his deſerved end, being executed at Claremont in Auvergne. Three days were ſpent in rifling houſes, and finding out thoſe that were ſuſpected: which being done on Friday 4 Kalends of VII br. <hi>Duperacus</hi> (a Citizen of Lions,<note place="margin">Auguſt 29th. Conchiliato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum equitum torque dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> but lately advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the order of Knighthood: the honour of this order for many years being decayed, ſince it began to be beſtowed upon unworthy perſons) came from the Queen with inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and letters of credence, bringing alſo letters from Claudius Rubius, and other City Officers, men of like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who managed the affairs of Lions at Paris, and in the Court; in which (letters) is declared what was done at Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, and withal it was added, that the King did will and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that the men of Lions ſhould follow the example of the Pariſians. Mandelotus, a prudent man, though he was looked upon as enclined to the Guiſian faction, abhorred the barbarouſneſs of the thing, and obtaining of the urgent mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude ſome days truce, till he had deliberated upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and till letters came from the King, which he ſaid he daily expected; in the mean time he made open Proclamation, that the Proteſtants ſhould repair to the Major's houſe to hear from him what was the King's pleaſure. They poor wretches coming out of their hiding places, as if they had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the King's protection, came to him, and by his command were committed to ſeveral priſons; for the King's priſons upon the River Rhone were not able to receive ſuch a multitude.<note place="margin">Rodanenſes Regii.</note> Upon this, <hi>Petrus Antiſſiodorenſis</hi> Chamberlain of the City, a man wicked and infamous for diſhoneſt luſts, rode poſt, and without letters, as if the dignity of the man had carried authority enough with him, affirms to Mandelotus, that this was the Kings and Queens will and pleaſure, that the Proteſtants that were taken, or could be taken, ſhould be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151791:32"/>ſlain, without expecting any further command. Therefore Mandelotus being overcome by the importunity of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude that ſtood round about him, to whom Antiſſiodorenſis had told the ſecret, yieldeth, and turning to the meſſenger of ſo horrid a ſentence, I will, ſaith he, ſay to thee Peter, what Chriſt heretofore ſaid to Peter; whatſoever thou bindeſt, let it be bound; and whatſoever thou looſeſt, let it be looſed; and preſently all ran to the ſlaughter and ſpoil, <hi>Morniellus</hi> and <hi>Clavius,</hi> wicked men, and ready for any miſchief, joyned themſelves to Boidomus. When they would have had the help of <hi>the Common Hangman</hi> in that matter, he refuſed, and ſaid that he was ready to obey the ſentence of a lawful Magiſtrate, but he would not meddle nor trouble himſelf with ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous executions: when the ſame thing was commanded, <hi>the guards</hi> of the Caſtle, they likewiſe being much moved at the motion, anſwered with diſdain, that they were no Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nor did ſuch diſhonourable employment become Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: thoſe miſerable men never injured them: therefore they hired men from the Shambles, and ſhameleſs perſons out of the dregs of the people; [but neither would they do it;] at length all theſe deteſting the fact, they came to the City Train-Bands, which confitted of 300 Townſmen, who did readily undertake againſt their own fellow-Citizens, what hangmen and ſtrangers had reſolutely refuſed. Out of theſe Bands therefore are choſen all the verieſt rake-hells, and they leading on, they ran violently to the houſe of the Franciſcans, (this was done upon the following Lord's-day) where part of the Proteſtants were kept, and then to the houſe of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtines, where a great ſlaughter was made: whiles Mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotus, with <hi>Sallucius Manta</hi> Governor of the Caſtle, ran with all ſpeed to the tumult raiſed by the people in the ſuburbs next the River Rhone, they make an aſſault upon the Arch-Biſhop's houſe, where 300 chief Proteſtants were, by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor's order kept in priſon: and firſt carefully examining their purſes, they moſt barbarouſly ſlew them, praying unto God, and imploring the ſaith of men. A miſerable ſad ſight!<note place="margin">Supplices &amp; Dei homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fidem implorantes.</note> while the Sons hanging about the necks of their Fathers, and Fathers embracing their Sons, Brethren, Friends, exhorting
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151791:33"/>one another to conſtancy, they were ſlain like ſheep by merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Butchers, Porters, Water-men, among the ſad lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and horrid cries that did reſound all over the City. Which thing Mandelotus in all haſte returning from Guilloteria, but yet after the thing was done, ſeemed to be much troubled at, as if it had been done without his conſent or privity; and coming to the place of the Maſſacre, taking the King's Officer along with him, that he might enquire into the matter in a legal way, and proofs being taken by a publick Notary, in a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous diſſimulation, he commanded Proclamation to be made, that thoſe that knew who were the Authors of this outrage, ſhould tell their names, an hundred Crowns being propoſed to the informer and diſcoverer for his reward. In the evening the ſame Butchers went to the publick priſon, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Rhone, and raged againſt the priſoners with a new ſort of cruelty; and miſerably tormented them with halters put about their necks, and dragged them half dead into the River that was near. The night following is ſpent in ſlaughters and plundering; houſhold-ſtuff is carried out of houſes, and wares out of ſhops: thoſe that hid themſelves are by ſpies brought out of their hiding places, and many thrown into the River. Mandelotus being offended at the horror of the ſight of the bodies of the ſlain lying in the Court of the Arch-Biſhop's houſe, commanded them to be put into boats, and carried to the other ſide of the River, that they might be buried in the Church-yard of the Monaſtery of Aiſnay, where was formerly the Altar of Lions, and ſent men thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſee them buried. But the Monks ſaid they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuffer that, and that thoſe carkaſſes were unworthy of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial. Therefore, upon a ſign given, there is a concourſe made, and they are thrown by the enraged people into the River; the groſſer bodies being given to the Apothecaries, upon their deſir, for their fat, as is reported by thoſe who wrote whiles things were freſh. Nor did the ſlaughter ſlay here. For not long after the (two) Brothers, <hi>Darutii,</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of great account, <hi>Labeſſaeus, Galterus,</hi> and <hi>Floccardus,</hi> honourable Citizens, being brought out of the priſon, had their throats cut, and were caſt into the River Rhone.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151791:33"/>Among theſe ſlaughters ſome <hi>eſcaped</hi> by the help of the guards, and the favour of Manta the Governor, among whom were <hi>Jo. Ricaldus,</hi> and <hi>Antonius Callia,</hi> Paſtors of the City, when as <hi>Joannes Anglus,</hi> chief Paſtor, was ſlain in the firſt tumult. It is ſaid that 800 of all kinds and ſexes were bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly ſlain: the carkaſſes of the ſlain ſwimming down Rhone to Turnonium, lay ſo thick about the banks, that the Townſmen affrighted at the accident, cried Arm, Arm, as if the enemy had been coming upon them: by and by being amazed with horror, and deteſting the authors of ſuch a vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, though they had no favour for the Religion of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, to remove that ſad ſpectacle, they ſet men to thruſt the bodies off with poles from the banks, which the ſwift ſtream brought down. So horrid a ſpectacle they alſo deteſted at Vienne, at Valence, at Burgh, at Viviers, at the Temple of the Spirit, yea, at Avenion, where there is great hatred of the Proteſtants. But at Arles, when through want of wells and ſprings they drink of the water of the River; the Townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, beſides the deteſtableneſs of the villany, were grievouſly diſtreſſed; when as they would not uſe the fiſhes and water that they could be ſupplied with only from Rhone; yea, they abhorred the very ſight of the River.</p>
            <p n="28">28. But in Dauphine and <hi>Provence</hi> things were carried af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter far another manner. For <hi>Claudius Sabaudus Count of Tende,</hi> who was very nearly allied to the Momorancies, when Letters were brought him about the ſame buſineſs by <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus Bonifacius Mola,</hi> who two years after came to an<note n="†" place="margin">Being execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and his quarters ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the City<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy end at Paris, ingenuouſly anſwered that he did not think that that was the King's pleaſure, but that ſome that were evilly affected to the publick Peace, did falfly pretend his name, when as not many days ſince he had received quite other commands: that therefore he would rather obey the former, as more worthy of the King's Faith and Clemency. But he not long after being at Avignon, died of a ſudden diſeaſe, to the great grief of the people of Provence, not without ſuſpition given him by the Emiſſaries of the ſeditious.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Dauphine, Bertrandus Simienus Gordius,</hi> educated in the Family of the Momorancies, receiving the ſame command,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151791:34"/>he excuſed himſelf, pretending the great danger he was like to be in from the powerfulneſs of Mombranius, and other Proteſtants in<note n="*" place="margin">In allobro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus.</note> Savoy and Dauphine, yet ſome were ſlain at <hi>Valence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo at <hi>Romans</hi> there were ſome ſlain, though it were late firſt,<note place="margin">Septembr. 22.</note> viz. 10 Kal. VIII br. where, when many of that great number that was caſt into the priſon, for fear of death retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Religion of their Anceſtors, only ſeven were ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with daggers by the raging people.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Santeranus</hi> Governor of <hi>Auvergne,</hi> who alſo was well affected to the Momorancies, uſed the ſame moderation, and made the ſame anſwer to thoſe that came poſting to him from Court, that the Count of Tende had done before him, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this moreover, that he would never obey ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, unleſs the King in perſon did command him.</p>
            <p>Greater was the fury that did rage at <hi>Tholouſe:</hi> for news of what had been done at Paris being brought prid. Kal. VII br. which was the Lord's-day,<note place="margin">Auguſt. 31.</note> upon which the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants went out of the City to Caſtanetum to Sermon, ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Gates were ſhut up, and care was taken that no one ſhould go out, but that whoſoever would might come in. But many of thoſe that had gone out would not return into the City, but went thence to<note n="†" place="margin">Podium Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentii.</note> le Puy, St. Laurence, Montau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,<note n="*" place="margin">Regium montem.</note> Regimont, and ſome one way, ſome another. Two days after, by authority of the Senate, publick Proclamation was made, that no violence or moleſtation ſhould be offered to the Proteſtants. The day following, Guards being ſet at the Gates of the City, and in the Streets, thoſe that were ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted are ſome of them diſtributed into Monaſteries, others are caſt into the common priſons; ſome days after, upon the coming from Court of <hi>Delpechius</hi> and <hi>Madronius,</hi> rich Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and moſt bitter enemies to the Proteſtants, they were all thrown into the Palace priſon, where preſently in the night, by certain cut-throats choſen out of the Students of the Civil Law, that went to the Fencing-School, (among whom one <hi>Turrius</hi> was moſt eminent), together with other men of lewd life and converſation, 200 were barbarouſly ſlain, and among them ſome Senators, and in the firſt place
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151791:34"/>
               <hi>Johannes Coraſius:</hi> who afterwards, to double their cruelty, were hanged in their Senatorian habits, upon an Elm grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Palace-yard: the bodies of the dead were buried in a ditch made in the Arch-Biſhop's houſe.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time, but with greater ſlaughter, were things carried at <hi>Rouen,</hi> where <hi>Tanaquilius Venator Carrugius,</hi> the Governor of the chief Nobility of Provence, a man of a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful diſpoſition, did what he could to hinder it. But at laſt, not being able any longer to withſtand the violence of the ſeditious, (and eſpecially of thoſe who, the year before, were, by the decree of the Judges, delegated from Paris, proſcribed, who hoped that, by this courſe, they ſhould both revenge the injury offered them, and alſo obliterate the memory of the Decree), many were thrown into priſon,<note place="margin">Septemb. 17.</note> and afterwards 15 Kal. of VIII br. being called out one by one by the voice of the Cryer, were cruelly ſlain by thoſe Emiſſaries, <hi>Maronimus</hi> a moſt wicked wretch leading them on. Upon this they ſet upon private houſes, and that day and the day following they fell upon men &amp; women, without diſtinction, and 500 of both ſexes and all ages were ſlain, and their bodies being ſtripped, were caſt into the ditches ad Portam Caletenſem, and their garments all bloudy as they were, were diſtributed among the poor, they ſeeking even by theſe murders to ingratiate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the people. This the Senate was in ſhew offended at, and began to proceed againſt the Authors of this fact: but through connivance it came to nothing, the murderers and cut-throats for a time ſlipping out of the City.</p>
            <p>This example raged through <hi>other Cities,</hi> and from Cities to <hi>Towns and Villages;</hi> and it is reported by many, that<note n="†" place="margin">It was Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly reported that there were ſlain above <hi>40000</hi> Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots in a few days, <hi>ſaith</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vila, p. <hi>376.</hi>
               </note> more than thirty thouſand were <hi>ſlain</hi> in thoſe tumults throughout the Kingdom, by ſeveral ways; though I believe the number was ſomewhat leſs.</p>
            <p>[<hi>In September,</hi> Caſtres, <hi>a City in la Paix Albigeois, which was held by the Proteſtants, when after great promiſes by the King for their ſafety, it was delivered into the hands of Creuſeta one of the principal of the neighbouring Gentry, it was by him cruelly plundered, and laid waſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:151791:35"/>
            <p>[<hi>In the beginning of October happened</hi> the Maſſacre at Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux. <hi>The Author and chief Promoter of it is reported to have been one</hi> Enimundus Augerius, <hi>of the Society at Claremont, who alſo is ſaid to have perſwaded Franciſcus Baulo, a very rich Senator of Burdeaux that he ſhould leave his wife; and being ſupported by his wealth, he had founded a rich School in that City: He, when as he did in his Sermons daily inflame his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, that after the example of the Pariſians they ſhould dare to do ſomething worthy of their piety: ſo eſpecially upon S. Michael's day, when he treated of the Angels, the miniſters of the grace and vengeance of God, what things bad been done at Paris, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leance, and other places, he did again and again, by often repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Speeches, inculcate, to have been done by the Angel of God; and did both openly and privately upbraid</hi> Romanus Mulus <hi>the King's Solicitor, and</hi> Carolus Monferrandus <hi>Governor of the City men of his faction, as dull and cold in this buſineſs, who contented themſelves to have interdicted the Proteſtants the liberty of meeting together, and to have kept the Gates of the City with guards; but otherwiſe they wholly abſtained from violence and ſlaughters, being admoniſhed ſo to do, as is believed by Stozzius, who had a deſign upon Rochel &amp; who did fear, leſt that ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his attempts. But when as about that time</hi> Monpeſatus <hi>came to</hi> Blaye, <hi>as though the ſign for effuſion of bloud had been given by his coming, certain men were ſlain in that Town. But when he arrived at Burdeaux, the people began to rage, and the ſeditious to run up and down.</hi> Enimundus thundered in his Preaching <hi>more than ever: at laſt, after ſome days private diſcourſes of</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſatus <hi>with</hi> Monferrandus, <hi>though it be uncertain whether he did diſcourage or perſwade the thing, when</hi> Monpeſatus <hi>was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, (who) a little while after died of a Bloudy Flux. V Non. VIII br. which fell upon a Friday,<note place="margin">Octobr. 3.</note> the Magiſtrates of the City with their Offcers, as they were ſent, came after dinner to the houſe of</hi> Monferrandus, <hi>bringing with them lewd &amp; impudently wicked men, who were drawn together by</hi> Petrus Leſtonacus, <hi>and receiving the word of command from him, they ran through the City to the ſlaughter, being diſtinguiſhed by their red Caps, a ſign very agreeable to their bloudy deſign. They began with</hi> Joannes Guillochius, and Gul. Sevinus, <hi>Senators, who were both cruelly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151791:35"/>murdered in their houſes, which were preſently rifled. Alſo</hi> Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherus <hi>the Senator, who had redeemed his life of Monferrandus for a great ſum of mony, did hardly eſcape the danger, whoſe houſe was alſo plundered. Then promiſcuous ſlaughters and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines are committed for three days together throughout the City, wherein</hi> two hundred ſixty four <hi>men are ſaid to be</hi> ſlain, <hi>and the Maſſacre bad been much greater, had not the Caſtle of Buccina and the other Caſtle of the City yielded an opportune place of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge to many.</hi> Jacobus Benedictus Longobaſtonus <hi>Preſident of the Court was in great danger of death, and was hardly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the help of his friends.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="29">29. Nor were they in the mean time in quiet at Paris and at Court, where, by the Queens ſpecial command, and the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of Morvillerius, <hi>Coligny's Cabinet</hi> was <hi>examined,</hi> if by any means they might find any thing in them which, being publiſhed, might take off the odium of ſo bloudy a fact either in the Kingdom or with foreign Princes. Among thoſe Commentaries which he did every day diligently write, which were afterwards deſtroyed by the Queens command, there was a paſſage in which he adviſed the King that he ſhould be ſparing in aſſigning the hereditary portion, which they call Appennage, to his Brethren, and in giving them authority, which having read, and acquainting Alanſon with it, whom ſhe had perceived to favour Coligny; This is your beloved cordial friend, ſaith the Queen, who thus adviſed the King. To whom Alanſon anſwered, <q>How much he loved me, I know not; but this advice could proceed from none but one that was faithful to the King, and careful for his affairs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Again, there was among his papers ſound a breviate, wherein, among other reaſons that he gave for the neceſſity of a War with the Spaniards in the Low-Countreys, this was added, as being omitted in the Speech which he made to the King, leſt it ſhould be divulged, and therefore was to be ſecretly communicated to the King, that if the King did not accept of the condition that the Low-Countreys offered, he ſhould<note n="†" place="margin">V. Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's Letter 14 Septemb. 1572. in the Compleat Ambaſſador, p. 241.</note> not transfer it to his neighbours of England, who, though they were now, as things ſtood, friends to the King, if
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151791:36"/>once they ſet footing in the Low-Countreys and the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces bordering upon the Kingdom, would reſume their former minds, and being invited by that conveniency, of friends would become the worſt enemies to the King and Kingdom. Which being likewiſe imparted to Walſingham, Queen Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeths Ambaſſador, and the Queen telling him, that by that he might judge how well Coligny was affected towards the Queen his Miſtreſs, who ſo much loved him. He made her almoſt the ſame anſwer, and ſaid, <q>He did not know how he was affected towards the Queen his Miſtreſs; but this he knew, that that counſel did ſavour of one that was faithful to the King, and moſt ſtudious of the honour of France, and in whoſe death both the King and all France had a great loſs.</q> So both of them, by almoſt the ſame anſwer, fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her womaniſh policy, not without ſhame unto her ſelf.</p>
            <p>About the end of the month wherein Coligny was ſlain, <hi>the King</hi> fearing leſt the Proteſtants ſhould grow deſperate in other Provinces, <hi>writes to the Governors with</hi> moſt ample com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and principally to <hi>Feliomrus Chabolius</hi> Preſident of Burgundy,<note place="margin">Carnii Comes.</note> in which he commanded that he ſhould go through the Cities and Towns that were under his juriſdiction, and friendly convene the Proteſtants, and acquaint them with the tumult at Paris, and the true cauſes thereof. <q>That nothing was done in that affair through hatred of their Religion, or in prejudice to the favour that was granted them by the laſt Edict: but that he might prevent the conſpiracy made by Coligny and his confederates againſt the King, the Queen, the King's Brethren, the King of Navar, and other Princes and Nobles. That it was the King's pleaſure that his Edicts might be obſerved, and that the Proteſtants every where taking forth Letters of ſecurity from the Preſidents, ſhould live quietly and ſafely under the King's protection, upon pain of death to any that ſhould injure or moleſt them in any thing. On the other hand, he ſhould admoniſh the Proteſtants that they ſhould keep themſelves quiet at home; and becauſe in their Meetings and publick Aſſemblies there uſed to be ſuch Counſels among the Proteſtants as were ſuſpitious to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151791:36"/>Catholicks, and which might put them upon new ſtirs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that they ſhould abſtain from thoſe meetings, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the ſame favour and ſafety from the King's clemency and goodneſs as he doth exerciſe towards others. But if they ſhould fooliſhly neglect this advice, command and promiſe of the King, and ſhould preſume to meet publickly, ſtir up troubles, and take up Arms under colour of their own defence, he would then proceed againſt them as againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels.</q> To the ſame effect were Letters ſent to <hi>Melchior Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſatus,</hi> Preſident of Poictou, <hi>Pria</hi> Preſident of Toures, and the Preſidents of other Provinces. <hi>Chabolius</hi> managed his office with great prudence and moderation, having learnt that the Proteſtants, who had hitherto been exaſperated by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and cruelty of puniſhments, might be better reduced to their duty by clemency and mildneſs. And matters were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered without almoſt any bloud-ſhed in <hi>Burgundy;</hi> many returning either through fear, or of their own accord, to the Religion of their Anceſtors, renouncing the Proteſtant Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. Only <hi>Claromontius Travius</hi> of the prime Nobility, whoſe Siſter Helena Antonius Grammontanus had married, was, when the news was hot, ſlain <hi>at Dijon,</hi> in the abſence of Chabotius, by the people. Thoſe that were ſuſpected <hi>at Maſcon,</hi> being by the King's command apprehended and caſt into priſon by Philibertus, ſuſtained no further damage.</p>
            <p n="30">30. So foul a tempeſt in France being in ſome ſort allayed, and the liberty of killing and plundering repreſſed, when the more prudent, that yet no way favoured the Proteſtant party, did, upon the ſad thought of the preſent ſtate of things, by little and little, come to themſelves, and abhorring the fact, did curiouſly enquire into the cauſes of it, and how it might be excuſed, they thus judged, <q>That <hi>no example of like cruelty</hi> could be found <hi>in all Antiquity,</hi> though we turned over the Annals of all Nations. Theſe kinds of outrages had been confined to certain men, or to one place, and might have been excuſed by the ſenſe of injury newly offered, or their rage did only exerciſe it ſelf upon thoſe whom it was their intereſt to remove out of the way. For ſo by the command of <hi>Mithridates</hi> King of Pontus upon one meſſage, and the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151791:37"/>ſignification of one Letter 40000 Romans were ſlain in one day throughout all Aſia.<note place="margin">The Sicilian Veſpers.</note> So <hi>Peter King of Arragon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded 8000 French-men to be ſlain in Sicily, who had ſeized upon it in his abſence: But their caſe was far different from this: For thoſe Kings exerciſed their rage upon ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and foreigners, but this (King) upon his own ſubjects, who were not more committed to his power than to his faith and truſt. <hi>They</hi> were obliged no otherwiſe by their faith given than to the ſtrangers themſelves, but <hi>he</hi> was bound in a late league with his neighbouring Kings and Princes, to keep that Peace which he had ſworn to. <hi>They</hi> uſed no arts unworthy of royal dignity to deceive them, <hi>he</hi> for a ſnare abuſed his new engaged friendſhip, and the ſacred Nuptials of his own Siſter, whoſe wedding garment was even ſtained with bloud. Theſe are the vertues that uſe to be commended in Kings, Juſtice, Gentleneſs and Clemency; but ſavageneſs and cruelty, as in all others, ſo eſpecially in Princes uſe to be condemned. Famous through all ages was Publius Scipio, who was wont to ſay he had rather ſave one Citizen, than ſlay a thouſand enemies; and Antonius, who was called the Pious, did often uſe that ſaying. Kings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed have power of life and death over the Subjects of their Realm, but with this limitation, that they ſhould not proceed againſt them till their cauſe was heard upon a fair tryal. This rage and blindneſs of mind was ſent by God upon the French, as a judgment for the daily execrations and reproaches of the Deity, from which the King himſelf, ill educated by his Mother, and by thoſe Tutors that ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him, did not at all abſtain; the example whereof proceeding from the Court to the Cities, and from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the Country-Towns and Villages, they now at every third word, ſwore by the head, death, bloud, heart of God. Moreover, the patience of God was even wearied with their Whoredoms, Adulteries, and ſuch luſts as are not fit to be ſpoken. Laſtly, nature it ſelf doth now expoſtulate as it were with God for his ſo long patience and for bearance, nor could the Country of France any longer bear ſuch prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wickedneſs. For as for <hi>the cauſes</hi> which are <hi>pretended
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151791:37"/>againſt Coliguy,</hi> they are feigned with ſuch improbability, that they can hardly perſwade children, much leſs can they be proved. For how is it probable that Coligny ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into ſuch a conſpiracy within the walls of Paris, who though he were guilty before the Pacification, (to ſuppoſe that), yet certainly after the Edict, if indeed the publick Faith and the King's promiſes ought to be obſerved, he came to the King guiltleſs, altogether abhorring a Civil War, and ſolicitous only about the Belgick War? But whereas they ſay he conſpired after he had received his wounds, this hath leſs colour of truth. For how could Coligny that was indiſpoſed by two ſuch wounds, now grown old, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled in both his arms, one of which the Phyſitians talked of cutting off, riſe with three hundred young men that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended him, againſt an Army of ſixty thouſand men, that bare him deadly hatred, and that were well appointed with Arms? How could he in ſo little time conſult concerning ſo great and vaſt a deſign? for he lived hardly forty hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had received his wound, in which all conference was forbidden him by his Phyſitians. Then, had he been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of any crime, was he not committed to Coſſenius and his guards, and the paſſages being every where ſecured, was he not in the King's power, that he might in a moment, if it had ſo pleaſed the King, been thruſt into priſon? and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes being prepared, after the manner of judicial proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, might he not have been proceeded againſt in form of Law? Moreover, if Coligni with his Dependents and Clients had conſpired againſt the King, why muſt needs the reſt that were innocent, ſo many Noble Matrons and Virgins who came thither upon the account of the Marriage, ſo many great-bellied women, ſo many ancient perſons, ſo many bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridden perſons of both Sexes and all profeſſions, that were ignorant of theſe laſt counſels of Coligni, be comprehended in the ſame guilt? To whom doth it not ſeem abſurd and moſt ridiculous that Coligni ſhould at ſo unſeaſonable a time conſpire againſt Navar that profeſſed the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with him, and whom he had in his power for four
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151791:38"/>years together? Thus many did diſcourſe, and ſo they judged, that upon the account of this fact the French Name would for a long time labour under an odium and infamy, and that poſterity would never forget an act of ſo great unworthineſs.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Typographical Errors to be Corrected as followeth, in</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Hiſt. of the Maſſacre:</hi> Pag. 5. l. 1. Burleigh, l. 7. Coſmus, p. 7. l. 4. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, p. 8. l. 10. when he, l. 36. Palace near the Louvre, p. 12. l. 1. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, p. 13. l. 28. Antonius Marafinus Guerchius <hi>(without commas),</hi> ſo p. 14. l. 2. Rochus Sorbaeus Prunaeus, l. 7. Armanus Claromontius Pilius, l. 8. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninius, l. 26. racket, p. 18. l. 7. your Kingdom, p. 21. l. 9. as he did, p. 28. l. 11. Coſſenius, l. 36. Atinius, l. 37. Sarlaboux, p. 29. l. 5. Merlin the Miniſter, Coligny, p. 32. l. 32. Claromontius Marqueſs of Renel, p. 34. l. 19. Caumon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, p. 35. l. 25. Montalbertus Roboreus, Joach. Vaſſorius Cunerius, Rupius, Columbarius, Velavaurius, Gervaſius Barberius Francurius, p. 36. l. 15. Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Claromontius Pilius, l. 32. Bellovarius, l. 36. Durfortius Duracius, l. 37. Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macius &amp; Buchavanius, p. 40. l. 36. Perionius, p. 41. l. 13. Languages, <hi>who had pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate feuds and contentions with Carpentar,</hi> &amp; l. 22. to thoſe, l. 30. Roliardus, p. 43. l. 2. Sancomontius Sauromanius, l. 3. Bricomotius, p. 53. l. 33. Meletinus, p. 57. l. 17. Arles, where, l. 36. ſuſpition of poiſon given, p. 58. l. 2. Mombrunius, p. 62. l. 20. Helionorus Chabotius, p. 63. l. 11. Chabotius.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Hiſt. of the Powder-Plot:</hi> Pag. 8. l. 27. Harrington, p. 14. l. 30. deteſt, p. 15. l. 21. for wikes, r. <hi>de Vic,</hi> p. 16. in marg. So on the, p. 22. l. 27. dele Book entituled, l. 29. for Provincial, r. <hi>Father General.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151791:38"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
